<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a clergy-man in the country to the clergy-man in the city, author of a late letter to his friend in the country shewing the insufficiency of his reasons therein contained for not reading the declaration / by a Minister of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1369A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26839</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09566518</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09566518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1334:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a clergy-man in the country to the clergy-man in the city, author of a late letter to his friend in the country shewing the insufficiency of his reasons therein contained for not reading the declaration / by a Minister of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Jones and published by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Halifax, George Savile, --  Marquis of, 1633-1695. --  Letter from a clergyman in the city to his friend in the country.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II). --  His Majesties gracious declaration to all his loving subjects for liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43628:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43628:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A Clergy-Man in the Country, TO The Clergy-Man in the City, Author of a late Letter to his Friend in the Country: SHEWING The Inſufficiency of his Reaſons therein contained for Not Reading the DECLARATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Miniſter of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>LICENSED, <hi>Aug.</hi> 15. 1688.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Savoy:</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw. Jones;</hi> and Publiſhed by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near Stationers-Hall. 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43628:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43628:2"/>
            <head>TO My Brethren of the Clergy IN THE COUNTRY,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat I here preſent you, is written with an hearty deſire to ſerve you: How you will accept it, I know not. I have been by ſome ſuſpected, and by others called <hi>Papiſt,</hi> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but now and then talking what is contained in this Book; which when you read, you will find juſt ſo impertinently, as you all of the <hi>Loyal Clergy</hi> were called ſo heretofore, when you offered to ſpeak but a word in Vindication of the Rights and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of <hi>CHARLES the Second,</hi> againſt the Popular Miſpriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe Days.</p>
            <p>It is not the <hi>Religion,</hi> but the Kings late <hi>Declaration</hi> is the Subject of this Diſcourſe. When the Order came firſt out, and was read in the <hi>Gazettes,</hi> I was frequently in the Company of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Clergy-Men; and once with a great concourſe of them, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening juſt about that time to be met together on a Publick Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The thing was talked, but no Man that I heard made any ſcruple of Reading it, as we were commanded. But ſoon after, we were attacked with a Letter from a Clergy-Man of the City, which of a ſudden enlightned our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, and let us ſee how dull our Country Apprehenſions were. Alas! till then we
<pb facs="tcp:43628:3"/>could eſpy nothing in it, againſt our Conſciences, againſt our Oaths, againſt the Laws both of God and Man, and to the utter and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Ruine of our Church. I was ſomewhat aſhamed for my ſelf, and the reſt of my Country-Brethren, that we ſhould all Balk this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the City-Divine. This made me caſt my Eye over the <hi>Declaration</hi> again, with a ſurvey alſo of his <hi>Letter:</hi> The reſult of my Thoughts on both is contained in theſe following Sheets. That Loyalty towards my <hi>King,</hi> which from my Childhood I ſucked in, and from the Breaſts of our Mother the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and which, I think, can never be era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated in me, has made me wonder at this, which ſeems to me L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vity of ſo many of the Clergy in this Matter. Our firſt Thoughts, were very ſudden; Let us ſtay a little, and conſider with our ſecond Thoughts. If I have herein done any thing which may be ſerviceable to you for that purpoſe, I think I have ſerved <hi>God</hi> and my <hi>King</hi> withal, and am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Loving Brother.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43628:3"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM A Clergy-Man in the Country, TO The Clergy-Man in the City, Author of a late Letter to his Friend in the Country: SHEWING The Inſufficiency of his Reaſons therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for not Reading the <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shall as freely and as friendly communicate my Thoughts to you concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Matter and Attempt of your Letter, as you have profeſſed to do the ſame to your Friend in the beginning of it, and for the ſame Reaſon you add, namely,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this is not a time to be reſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though with reſpect to His Majeſty and His Affairs of State, perhaps there never was more Reaſon and Prudence of our being reſerved in this Juncture:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43628:4"/>Yet with reſpect to this Attempt, in which you would engage the whole Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy with your unhappy Self, and communicate your Contagion in the City to us of the Country, it is otherwiſe. Like the dumb Son of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> this would make a Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> now ſpeak, who never ſpake before; to ſee that fatal Stab, which, by this Letter, and Diſcourſes of this kind, is aim'd at the very Heart of his Mother, and that Doctrine by which ſhe would ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize Her ſelf among other Chriſtian Churches, owning Her King next and immediately under God, in all Matters Eccleſiaſtical as well as Civil, Her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head and Governor.</p>
            <p>You have, Sir, in this your Letter, as an unnatural Member, riſen up againſt your Head, charged your Dread Sovereign with the breach of the Laws both of God and Man: You have rendred Him a Perſon not fit to be truſted; a Perſon deceitful, and deſigning the Ruine at the ſame time of thoſe He has promiſed to protect and maintain: You have kicked againſt His Sacred Authority and Power, to which God has commanded every Soul, on pain of Damnation, to be ſubject; and you have attempted to draw the whole Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy into the ſame Diſobedience and Damnation with your ſelf; and that in an Inſtance ſo trifling, as makes us at once the Wonder and Deriſion of ſuch Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Ambaſſadors as are now reſident in the Engliſh Court, whoſe report to their Maſters of ſuch an unprecedented Inſolence in us, will alarm all other Princes to a watchful Jealouſie over Men of our Order throughout the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World.</p>
            <p>As for the moſt Reverend the Archbiſhop, and the Right Reverend the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops concerned with him in this Matter: The fear and doubt, the haſte and ſurprize, the Induſtry and Vigilancy of a Party diſcontented, and ſubtile to ſtep in, and for their Intereſt to blow the Coals of this Conteſt; then the Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Threats of a Popular Faction, the falſe Friends, the inceſſant Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations, giving them reſt neither Day nor Night; the crafty laying hold of a new Matter aliene from the firſt, <hi>viz. The Defence of their Peerage,</hi> &amp;c. may excuſe <hi>à tanto,</hi> our Reverend Fathers, who unhappily fell under theſe Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: And much more the recoil, which I have heard is ſince upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of ſome of them, for what has fallen out on this occaſion contrary to their Expectations.</p>
            <p>But as for you, and the reſt of us to whom you direct your Letter, being under no ſuch Temptations, and having more Time and Repoſe, and none of thoſe Impediments of adviſing better with our ſelves and our Friends; and the after Wiſdom alſo of reflecting upon the Evils which have already enſued, and the many others like to ſpring out of this Root; I think our more prudent, charitable and Chriſtian Courſe, ſhould now have been, and I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it is the advice of the Biſhops themſelves, in ſtead of further inflaming, to caſt Water upon this Fire, which is ſo unhappily kindled between us and our Gracious King.</p>
            <p>None of them have yet publiſhed in Print any thing of their Manage and Conduct of this Buſineſs againſt the King, and I hope never will, how much ſoever they are ſollicited to do it; They had rather, as it ſeems, not have been neceſſitated to own, what was produced in Court, as their Addreſs or Petition
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43628:4"/>to His Majeſty in this Matter; and I believe do give their Bleſſings rather to thoſe Sons who cover, than expoſe, their Fathers Nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I have ſome cauſe to think, you are no Advocate of their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; you are of too hot a Head, and too much on the Laſh, to be theirs or our Charioter at this time: It is eaſily ſeen, whither you would drive us.</p>
            <p>If you are, as you pretend your ſelf, a Son of that Church, an unſpotted Loyalty has hitherto been accounted Her indeleble Character: I am ſorry to find ſo little of it in your Letter; you have by it outdone the ſubtilty and cruelty of all Her Enemies.</p>
            <p>Never was ſo deadly a ſtroke given, nor ſo natural and effectual to Her Ruine, as, that which you commend to us for the only method of ſaving Her.</p>
            <p>I am charitably minded you have done this nevertheleſs of a good Intent, crowded along with the zealous Hurry of a Popular Miſtake: And the rather, becauſe I ſee your Letter makes a better ending than a beginning; and that notwithſtanding your poſitiveneſs all the way, you are not ſo ſatisfied in your own Reaſonings, but you relent at laſt into that good Nature and Temper, which for your Honour, I will Remark in your own Words, thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This, Sir, is our Caſe in ſhort; the difficulties are great on both Sides; and therefore now, if ever, we ought to Beſiege Heaven, with our Prayers, for Wiſdom, Counſel and Courage, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear then the difficulties, which you acknowledge in this Caſe, I ſhall apply my ſelf, touching upon the moſt material parts of your Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Enemies,</hi> (you ſay) <hi>who have given our Gracious King this Council againſt us, have taken the moſt effectual way, not only to Ruine us, but to make us appear the Inſtruments of our own Ruine, that what courſe ſoever we take we ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and one ſide or other will conclude, we have undone our Selves and fall like Fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By our Enemies, I conceive, you can mean no other than the Kings Friends, whom I believe no further our Enemies, than what amounts to a bare <hi>Se De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where they meet us in oppoſition to what neceſſarily conduces to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Themſelves, their Lives, their Fortunes, you muſt not blame them but the common inſtinct of Nature, that they are ſo far our Enemies.</p>
            <p>In all other Caſes, they are our Friends, beyond our Expectations, Enemics ſhort, I am ſure, of our Fears, and of what was heretofore in publick Print, our own Character and Proſpect of a Popiſh Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>As for the Free and Undiſturbed Exerciſe of our Religion, our Churches, our Revenues, our Dignities, we enjoy them all: And we have further the Kings Gracious Offer, of whatſoever other Aſſurances we can excogitate againſt our Fears and Jealouſies, leſt they ſhould not continue.</p>
            <p>I know no cauſe of this great Out-cry againſt the King and His Friends, on account, that they are our Enemies, nor where we are hurt, unleſs by the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Hands, from flying at one anothers Throats.</p>
            <p>We are enabled by theſe Laws, ſo ſoon as we may, to let looſe our too prurient Rage, one upon the other, but eſpecially upon the Kings Friends, whom we, I think, therefore call our Enemies.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43628:5"/>
            <p>We can hardly forbear already and aloud, to foretell what muſt become of them afterwards, what Gibbets and Axes, and Confiſcations are provided for them; for His Majeſties Commiſſioners, Judges, Military Officers, Papiſts in Maſcarade and out of Maſcarade, and whoever elſe have not dared to deny their Obedience to His Majeſties Moral Commands, or to leave him Solitary and Deſtitute of Servants to Guard and Attend him,</p>
            <p>What elſe means this our ſo tenacious ſticking to theſe Undoing and Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Laws? And how pitifully are the Claws hid of ſuch, as pretend them to be the only poſſible expedient of their own Security?</p>
            <p>Now to repreſs the violent and blind Zeal of ſuch Men, for the Eſtabliſhed Laws, without abatement or allowance of any thing to the Viciſſitude, which the Providence of God has made among us, from a Proteſtant, to a Prince of the Catholick Communion, is, I aſſure my ſelf, all His Majeſty deſigns by His Endeavor to get our good Will, toward the remove of the Teſt and Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>And if I thought any Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or other of that Communion, compliant with the King in this his charitable undertaking, ſhould ſuffer in the leaſt Hair of his Head, or loſe by it any the leaſt Liberty becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian to own in ſuch a Juncture, I ſhould not have opened my Mouth to have been an Advocate in this Cauſe.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever thinks otherwiſe, if he conſider, he will find he cannot do it, without Reflection of moſt vile ill Names upon his Majeſties Honour, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the Sacredneſs of his Royal Promiſe.</p>
            <p>So that, Sir, I think, you might have ſpared His Majeſties Friends and His Council, and have allowed them a milder Character, than <hi>our Enemies, and ſuch as ſeek our Ruine;</hi> by that Name expoſing them in the very Head of your Letter, to the Rage and <hi>Odium</hi> of the People; who are ſo far from being Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to us, that themſelves are the Perſons in diſtreſs and danger from us.</p>
            <p>And having now a time to Speak, do requeſt of us, without any injury to our ſelves, that we will pleaſe to remove no other but thoſe Laws, to which not only their Fortunes, but their Lives lay every Hour Obnoxious, and only for ſerving God according to their Conſciences, and their King at his Command, according to their natural Allegiance.</p>
            <p>But theſe Enemies of ours, ſince you will have them ſo, you note further, and to our greater misfortune, to be of that baſe and ignoble kind, as having us in their Claws, they muſt divert themſelves a little in Play with us, as the Cat does with the Mouſe, before they devour us, our Gracious King the while looking on; and ſo comes in the buſineſs of the Declaration.</p>
            <p>The Reading of which in our Churches and Chapels, you intimate to be contrived as it were for nothing in the World but to make our Enemies Sport: For the main work of our Undoing you account is over, and the trick of this Declaration no other, <hi>Than while themſelves are the Authors, to make us appear nevertheleſs the Inſtruments of our own Ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In good earneſt, Sir, and is this the likelieſt reaſon you could Excogitate? Had you but a little of what St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>thinketh no evil,</hi> that would have ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to you ſome more charitable account of His Majeſties, together with his Councils proceeds in this Affair.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43628:5"/>
            <p>If you had not been ſo haſty, as to take what lay uppermoſt in a Mind poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with Paſſion and Prejudice, you might have thought of that His Majeſty Himſelf publiſhes in the front of His Declaration, in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Our Conduct has been ſuch in all times, as ought to have perſwaded the World, that We are firm and conſtant to Our Reſolutions: Yet that eaſie People may not be abuſed by the Malice of crafty wicked Men, We think fit to declare, That Our Intentions are not changed ſince the Fourth of <hi>April</hi> 1687. when We iſſued out Our Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience.</q>
            </p>
            <p>How the eaſie People have been wrought upon ſince that time, to leſſen their Opinion of His Majeſties Sincerity in that Declaration, is too notorious.</p>
            <p>And what Inſinuations of the daily progreſs and advance towards the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling them under the Yoak of Popery and Arbitrary Power, nevertheleſs for the Kings Promiſe and Declaration of Liberty, and all this not only from the Preſs, but many of the Pulpits too.</p>
            <p>To obviate which Malice of theſe crafty wicked Men, His Majeſty, with His Council, have thought expedient, to iterate his Declaration, and to extend the Publication of it to all Churches and Chapels, which was omitted before, becauſe His Majeſty never imagined to have met with ſo much of it among the Men of Churches and Chapels, as ſince He hath found.</p>
            <p>This has made it at length neceſſary, by the Reading of it in Churches and Chapels, to undeceive the eaſie People there alſo.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, why may not this Account ſatisfie you, which appears ſo ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and probable, without raiſing up the Old Cry of Forty One, againſt the King and His Evil Council, and expoſing His Miniſters of State on every ſlight Occaſion? And why ſhould you affright your ſelf and your Readers, with ſo many falſe Alarms of <hi>Enemies,</hi> of <hi>Ruine,</hi> of <hi>falling,</hi> of <hi>unavoidable undoing what courſe ſoever we take;</hi> and require us to give more Credit to your melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Dreams, than to the Honour and Integrity of His Majeſty, and the open Declaration of His innocent Meaning?</p>
            <p>After which, I do agree with you, that ſhould we chuſe to take our fall here, and die of mere conceit, we do leave a ſhrewd Temptation upon ſome to conclude as you ſay, <hi>That we have undone our ſelves, and die like Fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems though in the next Paragraph, you have found a more honourable and comfortable way of falling, as ſuppoſe <hi>for refuſing to read Maſs, or to ſwear to the Trent Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I agree with you in this, but wonder then, that you, who can ſee ſo well, and approve the better, and are ſo confident it is not far off, ſhould undertake to perſwade the Church of <hi>England</hi> to fall before-hand with you, and to die with a <hi>Deteriora ſequor</hi> over her Tomb, for her Epitaph.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this of falling for refuſing to read Maſs,</hi> you ſay, <hi>is not our preſent caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, nor ever ſhall be in future, if His Majeſty may be believed, and His Meaſures taken and complied with by our ſelves.</p>
            <p>You ſhall never have the Honour, Sir, to fall ſo in His Reign, nor in any to follow, if His Declaration be ſuffered to take the effect.</p>
            <p>But one thing there is by the way, which I cannot paſs over without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark; which is,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43628:6"/>
            <p>That though this Declaration have two Strings, and tuned harmoniouſly one to the other, yet quite through this your Letter you can never be made to ſtrike both together.</p>
            <p>One is, His Majeſties Deſire of our Compliance with Him for taking off the Teſt and Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>The other is, His Declaration in the firſt place, <q>That he will Protect and Maintain our Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and Clergy, and all other His Subjects of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the free exerciſe of their Religion as by Law eſtabliſhed, and in the quiet and full enjoyment of all their Poſſeſſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Moleſtation or Diſturbance whatſoever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now upon one of theſe Strings you are perpetually harping, <hi>viz.</hi> The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the Penal Laws and Teſt; and that makes no Muſick alone, without the other, to a Church of <hi>England</hi> Ear, be it of the Nobility, Gentry or Clergy.</p>
            <p>It is certain, it would undo the Church of <hi>England</hi> to have her Teſt and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws taken away by a Parliamentary Law, without any Proviſion made by a like Parliamentary Law to ſecure the keeping what ſhe has beſide, and what the King has promis'd ſhall remain inviolate.</p>
            <p>This His Majeſty offers, and ſhould be always ſuppoſed along with the other: But that is the String you cannot be made to touch; and you are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Reaſon for it, for then you had anſwered your Letter your ſelf, and that had ſtopped the Mouth of all your popular, but falſly and temerariouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, Conſequences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to take away the Teſt and Penal Laws at this time, is but one ſtep from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing of Pepery; and therefore to read ſuch a Declaration in our Churches, though it do not immediately bring Popery in, yet it ſets open our Church-Doors for it, and THEN it will take time to enter, and THEN the People will hate us and deſpiſe us, and THEN we may be eaſily cruſhed, and THEN we fall without pity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe <hi>THENS</hi> hang upon the ſame String, and are but begg'd Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences. However, I perceive you are ſo confident of your Skill in linking a Chain of Conſequences, and hanging them on the Thread of a Spiders Web, that you are reſolved not to ſtay for the fulfilling of your Propheſie of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by the introducing of Maſs, <hi>Trent</hi> and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; but ſeeing it comes all to one, even as good fall now, it is but a little the ſooner, by not reading the Declaration.</p>
            <p>For this perſecuting Declaration does threaten us, that if we hold but our Hands from knocking His Majeſties Friends on the Head with our Penal Laws, then in the firſt place, <q>He will Protect and Maintain our Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Clergy, and all other His Majeſties Subjects of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the free exerciſe of our Religion as by Law eſtabliſhed, and in the quiet and full enjoyment of all our Poſſeſſions, without any Moleſtation or Diſturbance whatſoever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Matter is plain, What ſhould we live for any longer? But even die Marryrs with all the ſpeed we can, leſt if this Declaration ſhould take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, we never have opportunity to do it more. <hi>Let us ſuffer all that can be ſuffered,</hi> ſay you, <hi>in this World, rather than contribute to the final Ruine of the beſt Church in the World, by reading ſuch a Declaration as this.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43628:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But I think it is good firſt,</hi> as you ſay in the next Paragraph, <hi>to ſtay a little, and examine the Matter impartially, as thoſe which have no mind either to ruine themſelves, or to ruine the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that you may lay your Foundation ſure, you begin with a conjectural and precarious Suppoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſuppoſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>no Miniſter of the Church of</hi> England <hi>can give his Conſent to the Declaration:</hi> And with this <hi>Peſtulatum</hi> away you run to prove, Then he cannot read it.</p>
            <p>That this is a <hi>Non Supponendum,</hi> you ſee in the experience and event of the thing, ſome both Biſhops and Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do Conſent and Read it, and I doubt not but many more will, if His Majeſty think fit; Well, and what Fault have they committed? None at all, your ſelf being Judge. For you ſay,</p>
            <p>Pag. 4. <hi>Reading the Declaration would be no Fault at all, but our Duty, when the King Commands it, did we approve of the matter of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, with thoſe who can approve of the matter of it and Read, we have nothing to do here; they are acquitted by your ſelf; and they prove more, it ſeems, than you ſuppoſed, and if there be any Fault, it muſt remain to be on the part of thoſe, who do not Conſent nor Read.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, the Baſis or Ground-work, on which you Rear the whole Superſtructure of your Letter, is a ſuppoſition, That no Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can give his Conſent to the Declaration.</p>
            <p>What! Not to a thing in which, if there be any Fault, it is of his own making? Is our thinking ſome one way, ſome the other, enough to turn the Scale ſo, as what were otherwiſe no fault at all, becomes preſently contrary to the Laws of God, and Laws of the Land, as you ſay afterward?</p>
            <p>Point to that matter of the Declaration, which cannot be approved by a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> on account, of its being contrary to, or prohibited by, the Laws of God.</p>
            <p>This indeed <hi>would make it matter of Conſcience;</hi> which to render it the more odious, you here and there ſlily ſuggeſt, without offering at the leaſt mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Proof, for you know well enough there is none. His Majeſty by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Declaration, requires us to ſignifie to His People, a method, which in this juncture he Judges moſt expedient to be taken, for the ſecuring the Crown and the Perſons of our Kings, from thoſe apparent Dangers, to which they have been frequently expoſed by our Diſſentions in matters of Religion, and for the common Peace and Good of all His Subjects.</p>
            <p>Some approve it, and ſome do not, according as their Humour, their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or their Parts ſerve, and as ordinarily Mens Cenſures paſs on other Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of State.</p>
            <p>But ſo to Reprobate it as a <hi>Mulum in ſe,</hi> as a Peſt to the Publick, as an Abomination and Prophanation of our Churches, and not fit to be heard by Chriſtian Ears, is ſuch a hard ſtraining of the caſe, as brings along with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the very dregs of Paſſion and Party.</p>
            <p>We cannot approve of the matter of it, you ſay; it may be ſo, Men do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> always diſapprove or deny their Conſent to what is propoſed, becauſe it is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43628:7"/>evil, but becauſe they have no mind to it, and ſo the conſequence will be, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it to the matter in Hand: That the Authority of His Majeſty, over a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> does not to extend ſo far, as to injoyn him to Read the Declaration, when he has no mind to it: For, I doubt, there is with a great many, more of Stomach in the refuſal, than Conſcience; but this not to appear above board.</p>
            <p>One thing though I perceive you have a great mind to, which is, that we would grant you your ſuppoſition, before you prove it, namely,</p>
            <p>That no Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can give Conſent to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and then let you alone to make good your Inference, that he cannot Read it.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, I do not think you have us ſo much upon the Hanck as you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, ſhould I grant your Suppoſition.</p>
            <p>But I ſee you care not, whither we do or no, for you preſently fall hot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Work, to prove the Concluſion; <hi>Ergo,</hi> He cannot Read, for that is interpretative Conſent.</p>
            <p>Now for my part I confeſs to you, I turn over the Leaf, knowing how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoever your Arguments be to prove it, they would not ſatisfie me, nor I think any reaſonable Man, till he ſee firſt how well bottom'd your Hypotheſis be, from which you borrow your Inference.</p>
            <p>I would fain ſee your Reaſons firſt: Why a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> cannot Conſent, before I grant what you are ſo haſty to ſuppoſe.</p>
            <p>Why, that I ſhall by and by, but you will prove firſt, That Reading is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, Reading is Teaching, which is as odd an <hi>Hyſteron Proteron,</hi> as Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Trying afterwards.</p>
            <p>Let Reading be Conſenting or not Conſenting, without troubling your ſelf, till I hear whether I may Conſent or Not.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I muſt beg your Favour, to let me depart from your method, and turn over two or three Pages further, to examine your Reaſons wherefore we cannot Conſent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Your firſt is, That <hi>it is againſt the Conſtitution of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>which is eſtabliſhed by Law, and to which I have ſubſcribed; and therefore am bound to teach nothing contrary to it, ſo long as this Obligation laſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now a Proteſtant Church, diſtinct from what it was before, conſiſts in various Acts of Parliament, made eſpecially in the beginning of the Reformation: But I know of no Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required of the Clergy to ſuch Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>There is a Book intituled, <hi>Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical, Treated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Biſhop of</hi> London, &amp;c. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1603. Which Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical are in Number CXLI. Theſe I think you muſt mean, by your ſaying, <hi>to which you have ſubſcribed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you have not pleaſed to tell us againſt which of them it is we offend, by Reading the Kings Declaration: So that this Argument does nothing but lead us into a Wood, and there leave us to be loſt.</p>
            <p>Is there any Conſtitution or Canon Eccleſiaſtical which bars the King from extending Clemency even to His Diſſenting Subjects, where He ſees a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43628:7"/>and honourable Occaſion for it: Much leſs where the Neceſſity of His Affairs drive Him to it, His Honour, His Conſcience, the Preſervation of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and His Friends, and the common Peace of all; I dare truſt King <hi>JAMES</hi> the Firſt for that, without troubling my ſelf to look over all the Hundred and Forty One Canons. He had more King-craft, than to part with ſuch a Jewel out of the Crown, to adorn the Croſier of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſtitution you mention here, is to what you have ſubſcribed, you ſay.</p>
            <p>By the 36 Canon, Subſcription is required, not to the whole Book, but only to three Articles in that Canon mentioned.</p>
            <p>By the firſt, We acknowledge the Kings Supremacy. By the ſecond, The lawful uſe of the Common-Prayer. By the third, An Allowance is made of the 39 Articles. Upon any of which I cannot imagine how you ground your Reaſon, wherefore we cannot conſent to the Declaration, unleſs you had told us. If you were to prove the contrary from theſe Conſtitutions, there ſeems to be ſomething accommodate for your purpoſe in the firſt and ſecond Canons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are obliged by the firſt, to keep and obſerve all and ſingular the Laws made for reſtoring to the Crown of this Kingdom, the Antient Juriſdiction over the State Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which Antient Juriſdiction in the Second Canon is reſembled to the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, which the godly Kings had among the Jews and Chriſtian Emperors of the Primitive Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Parallel run ſo high as to the Antient Juriſdiction of this Crown, how Antient does it mean? Certainly before any pretence of the Invaſion of it by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherefore that being a Work too big for a Letter, I will give but one or two Inſtances, and thoſe ſo far back, as to be out of ſuſpicion of any ſuch Foreign Invaſion.</p>
            <p>The Government or Juriſdiction of this Crown, if inherent in it, was, and of right ought to be, the ſame in Matters of Religion, as well while that of our Princes and their Subjects was Pagan, as afterwards when it became Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Let us ſee then the Tranſition from the one Religion to the other in the Reigns of <hi>Lucius</hi> the Firſt <hi>Britiſh,</hi> and <hi>Ethelbert</hi> the Firſt Chriſtian King of the <hi>Saxons.</hi> We find that in both, our Kings acted without any controul of Laws, as well in the relinquiſhing the long-eſtabliſhed Pagan, as in the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian Religion. And as our Kings were free, ſo they kept their Subjects free from the Coaction of Laws in that Matter.</p>
            <p>Particularly Venerable <hi>Beda</hi> relates of <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> That having embraced the Chriſtian Religion, he could not but caſt ſome more benign Aſpect on ſuch as were Converts with himſelf. Yet ſo,<note place="margin">Bed. Hiſtor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. ex Verſione Abrahami Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock.</note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t nullum cogeret ad Chriſtianiſimum,</hi> That there ſhould be no Force upon the Conſciences of his Subjects. <hi>Didicerat enim à doctoribus, auctoribuſque ſuae ſalutis, ſervitium Chriſti voluntarium non coactitium debere eſſe.</hi> For that he had been taught of thoſe who were the Authors of his Salvation, That the Service of Chriſt ought to be voluntary, and not of compulſion.</p>
            <p>The Antient Juriſdiction of this Crown, you may ſee by this, was at that time free; and whatever Laws were before eſtabliſhed in favour of the Pagan
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43628:8"/>Superſtition, and Perſecution of Chriſtians, theſe Princes diſpenſed with them of their own Supreme Power, next and immediately under God, and ſo became Inſtruments of introducing the Bleſſed Means of Salvation, and tranſmitting them to us their Poſterity: Which otherwiſe perhaps had not been ſo eaſily effected by a National or Parliamentary Concurrence at preſent. But this Subject has been laboured, by many great and learned in the Laws of this Realm, to whom it eſpecially belongs, and to whom I refer thoſe who deſire further ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>This Antient Juriſdiction of the Crown, the Second Canon meaſures by that which was claimed and exerciſed of the godly Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and Chriſtian Emperors of the Primitive Church. How uncontrouled of any they exerciſed that Power who were Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> let their Hiſtory in the Holy Scriptures teach you.</p>
            <p>As for the Ancient Chriſtian Emperors, that they iſſued out Laws Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical by their Imperial Edicts, and made Revocation of thoſe Edicts as they pleaſed, I think no Body will deny. I know there was all the way of the Primitive Chriſtianity, another Spiritual Juriſdiction over Souls, and even over the Emperors themſelves, as they were Sons of the Church, for their Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but no way intrenching on the Temporal Power even in Cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, proper to ſuch a Power: When ever it made any attempt that way, it was always checked by Chriſtian Princes. And is it to be believed that this Canon, which was made, with all the ſingular Laws and Statutes there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for the aboliſhing all Foreign Power repugnant to the ſame, would not have been as ſharp upon any upſtart Power at Home, and of His Majeſties own Subjects repugnant to the ſame, if they had been aware of any the leaſt tendency then to ſuch an Inſolence? Take an Inſtance in one of the moſt famous and firſt Emperor of the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; and let us ſee what kind of Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical the Canons of our Church give to our Kings in parallel to what was exerciſed by the Chriſtian Emperors of the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Thrice, I think, according to ſome Hiſtorians, twice I am ſure according to <hi>Valeſius,</hi> in the Appendix to his Latin Verſion of <hi>Euſebius</hi> his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did diſpenſe with the Imperial Laws, by Indulgence and Toleration of the Donatiſts in <hi>Africa:</hi> And for that purpoſe cauſed his Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Indulgence to be publiſhed, directed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis Epiſcopis per Africam,</hi> to all the Biſhops throughout <hi>Africa,</hi> as it is found extant among the Writings of <hi>Optatus,</hi> and almoſt in the like words, and for the like Reaſons on which His Majeſty iſſued out this His preſent Declaration of Liberty: Some part of it I will therefore repeat: <hi>Quod fides debuit, quantum prudentia valuit, prout puritas potuit, tentaſſe me per omnia optimè ſcitis, ut juxta Magiſteria Legis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae Pax ſtabilita, per omnem concordiam teneret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sed quia vim illam ſcel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris infuſi — intentionis noſtrae ratio non potuit edo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nare — expectandum nobis eſt, dum totum hoc—Omnipotentis Dei miſericordia witigetur.— Verum dum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis Medicina procedat, hactenus ſunt cencilia noſtra Moderanda ut patientiam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colamus, &amp; quidquid inſolentia ilierum pro conſuetudine intemperantiae, tentat aut facit id omne tranquillitatis virtute toleremus, nihil ex reciproco reponatur injuriae,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43628:8"/>
            <p>This Declaration of Indulgence had likewiſe the ill fortune of His preſent Majeſties, to be regrated by ſome of the Churchmen, and the ſeverity of the eſtabliſhed Laws againſt the Donatiſts, ſom what unwillingly reſtrained, and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> by ſome of them, particularly by <hi>Caecilianus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited to revoke his Letters of Indulgence; whereupon, ſays the Hiſtorian, in the year 321. The Biſhops on the part of <hi>Donatus,</hi> put up their Petition al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the Emperor, <hi>Poſcentes ut libere ipſos agere ſineret, nec invitos adCommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem Caeciliani cogere vellet.</hi> Adding further, that they never ſhould, either by Promiſes or Threats, be induced to it, and that they would rather dye a thouſand deaths, than to hold. Communion with that Knave (as they rudely ſtyled the Biſhop) againſt their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>And here (as the Hiſtorian goes on) did moſt of all appear the Clemency of the Emperor; that when he ought to have puniſhed this impudence, and inſolence of the Donatiſts, in calling their Archbiſhop Knave, whoſe Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was well known and approved by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelf; <hi>Nihilominus ipſis quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſcebant ſolita benignitate indulſit.</hi> Nevertheleſs, of his wonted Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity he Granted what Indulgence they deſired; iſſuing out to <hi>Verinus,</hi> his <hi>(Vicarius)</hi> Vicar-General in <hi>Africa,</hi> a Reſcript, ſignifying his pleaſure, that the Donatiſts ſhould be recalled from Baniſhment; <hi>Monenſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ut proprio eos d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat arbitrio, ac furorem eorum Deo vindici reſervet,</hi> &amp;c. All this <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> did by the Virtue of that Authority, in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical; which the Godly Kings had among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Emperors of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, and, which ſays the Canon further, is the Regal Supremacy of this Crown, and by the Laws of this Realm therein eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> be the ſame it was then, you ſee by what meaſures we are to Govern ourſelves in the preſent Affair. Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Downe and Connor,</hi> I think, was a Man, who underſtood, how far a Church of <hi>England</hi> Loyalty ought to extend, as any Man this day of it; He ſays plainly in his <hi>Ductor Dubitantium, Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 148. That the Supreme Power is above the Laws; that he can diſpenſe with Laws, he can interpret them, and he can abrogate them, he can in time of neceſſity Govern by the Laws of Reaſon, without any written Law, and he is Judge of the neceſſity, and in all this he warrants him, as the Canon does, by the Power which the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> had; and, in the later end of that Chapter, ſays, that this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of Kings is not againſt Law, but by Law, and that the Laws them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves imply ſo much, and have given this leave. The ſame Loyal Biſhop in the ſaid Treatiſe further notes, the great ſubmiſſion which the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves made to the Imperial Laws, and that, even when they liked them, and when they lik'd them not; and of all, moſt material (ſays he) is the Obedience of <hi>St. Gregory</hi> the Great to <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperor. who made a Law, that no Soldier ſhould turn Monk without his leave. This <hi>St. Gregory</hi> eſteem'd to be an impious Law, he modeſtly admoniſhed the Emperor of the irreligion of it. But <hi>Maurice,</hi> nevertheleſs, commanded him to publiſh that Law. The good Biſhop knew his Duty, obeyed his Prince, ſent it up and down the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and gave this account of it: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trobi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quae debui exolvi, qui Imperat ri obedientiam praebui, &amp; pro Deo quod ſenſi minimè tacui.</hi> I have done both my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43628:9"/>Duties, I have declared my Mind for God, and have paid my Duty and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Emperor. <hi>Ductor Dubit. Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 176. This that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Loyal Biſhop remarks as a preſident to Guide and Govern Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the like Caſes. And by the way we may note upon the Story, that in thoſe days, when <hi>St. Gregory</hi> publiſh'd an Edict of the Emperor's, which, to him ſeemed impious, Reading was not thought to be Teaching. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that the model and meaſures of our Government are different, and will not admit of ſo high a Prerogative in our Princes, as was exerciſed in thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded and abſolute Monarchies.</p>
            <p>What! not in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical? Was it well done then of the Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops of our Church in Convocation, to run the parallel of that Obedience we owe to His Majeſty in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, up to the height of what was uſed <hi>by the Godly Kings among the Jews, and Chriſtian Emperors of the Primitive Church, and to hold him Excommunicate,</hi> ipſo facto; <hi>Whoſoever ſhould affirm the contrary, and not reſtored, but only by the Archbiſhop, after his Repentance, and publick Revocation of thoſe his wicked Errors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And had not you better have held your peace, than on this occaſion, to have medled with the Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which you have ſubſcribed. I think this a time to have been more reſerved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your Second Reaſon, wherefore we cannot Conſent, and conſequently not Read, follows;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe it is to Teach an unlimited, and univerſal Toleration, which the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in</hi> 72 <hi>Declared illegal, and which has been condemned in the Chriſtian Church in all ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How well you have reaſoned from the Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in ſuch points of it as relate to this matter, let others Judge. Your next proof is drawn from the Civil Conſtitution, with Reſpect to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> that ſays it is illegal.</p>
            <p>How, the Parliament of <hi>England?</hi> Where are the Three Eſtates, Where the King? Did all theſe Declare it illegal?</p>
            <p>I wonder you will ſo much reproach the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> with whom you deal in this Diſcourſe, as to think them ſuch as may be ſhammed again with the old Wheadle of 41. No, no, Sir, we know enough, and have felt enough, and too lately, yet to forget it, of ſuch Parliaments, as would have their Votes and Ordinances Obligatory to the Subject, without the Aſſent and Authority of the King: And yet this is the Authority, and the beſt you have to alledge, or ſay for yourſelf, in juſtification of your Diſobedience, and Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to His Majeſty in this Affair.</p>
            <p>The Parliament (ſay you) in 72. Declared it illegal; What then? What is the Parliaments Declaration to us in this, or in any other matter, ſo as to make it illegal, ever the more without the King? Is this after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of a Monarchical Government? Does not a pretence to ſuch a Power in a Parliament, without the concurrent Authority of the King, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom? But I aſſure myſelf, that they in that matter, aſſumed not to themſelves, ſuch a Power as your Letter would give them. Why may not a Vote of the Houſe of Lords and Commons in 41.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43628:9"/>the King diſſenting, be as good an Authority, as one in 72. the King diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? On the ſame grounds you may as well determine againſt the Kings So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and his Negative Voice, as his diſpenſing Power. For it was then reſolved, and while they were yet a legal Parliament, as that in, I mean that of 41. <hi>That the Sovereign Power reſides in both Houſes, and that the King ought to have no Negative Voice. Reſolved alſo, That whatſoever they Declared to be Law, ought not to be queſtioned by the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to theſe Votes the King never gave his Aſſent, wherefore they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing to us; but the Opinion of thoſe men, at that time: The Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power, and the Negative Voice, and the Authority of Declaring what is Law, and what is not Law, ſtanding where it did before, for all their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring otherwiſe then; or the Parliament in 72. Declaring afterward.</p>
            <p>But I humbly conceive (as I ſaid before) that the Parliament in 72. never meant to extend their Vote to the Uſes you have made of it in your Letter. The worſt which can be made of it, is no more than that the Queſtion being at that time moved about the Diſpenſing Power in the King, they ſhewed their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but left the matter remaining undertermin'd. For you muſt know, it was no more than the Opinion, and not the Sentence of Illegality, which was paſſed on the King's Diſpenſing Power at that time. They knew well enough that to be an Unparliamentary proceeding, and that they had no Authority to drive that buſineſs ſo far, without the joynt Concurrence of the King; only it is ſome Mens preſumption, or ignorance to give them more. Where there is a matter of Queſtion, or Doubt between the King and the Parliament; the Houſe, of Lords, or the Houſe of Commons, or both, having by the King's leave, the liberty of free ſpeaking there, may give their Judgment by paſſing a Vote, ſo as to incline to their Opinion, and obtain the Kings, if they can, to a Conſent, and Concurrence with them; but not, ſo as to bind the Subject, or to defend them in their Diſobedience to the King: In the mean time, till the matter be more Legally, and Authentically, according to the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws and Conſtitutions of this Kingdom determined; which can be no otherwiſe than with the joynt conſent of the King, and His two Houſes of Parliament together. Till then, however problematically illegal, the thing is not Authoritatively illegal, and ſo, however ſhaken by the Opinions of ſome Great Perſons, yet ſtill left ſtanding within the Verge of the King's Command, and the Subjects Obedience. For by the Fundamental Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and by a natural Allegiance to our Sovereign, and Union to him, as Members to our Politique Head, we are bound to obey the King, not only in all inſtances Legal, but in all matters not Illegal: Of which nature are all things, neither forbidden by God, nor by ſuch Perſons as have the ſufficient and plenary Authority to do the ſame, according to the Fundamental Laws and Conſtitution of this Monarchy; And of that nature is the Diſpenſing Power, which the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have always claimed to have over the Laws of their own, or of their Predeceſſors Enacting, in all ſuch Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as, with the change of Times and Circumſtances, they become deſtructive and noxious; as firſt, and principally to the Head, ſo to the other parts, which make up, together with Himſelf, the whole Body Politique.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43628:10"/>
            <p>It is ordinary for ſome diſcontented Perſons, diſcountenanced at Court, diſplaced from Office, defeated in their Expectations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to draw a Parry along with them, or to ſute themſelves to one formed to their hands, and by theſe, eſpecially in Parliaments, to ſhew their reſentments by their perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and croſsneſs to the King's Affairs; which nevertheleſs may be, and are for the moſt part fruſtrated, without any conſiderable detriment to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, through the wiſe Conſtitution of this Kingdom, which ſoon leaves theſe weak and ſpiteful Efforts to turn to nothing but froth, and bubble, wanting the Support and Authority of the Royal Aſſent.</p>
            <p>But how diſingenious, and diſagreeing to Men, eſpecially of our Order, is it? to rake into the aſhes of ſuch long ſince departed Feuds and Factions, and to raiſe up again, what Time and Oblivion had buried, to ſerve us in this Cauſe againſt the King.</p>
            <p>If we meaſure and form our Obedience by ſuch Precedents, and make ſuch Votes of Parliament ſerve inſtead of Laws, when our Intereſt wants them. What hints will others be apt to take from our examples, and perhaps, when they want a better Reaſon for their Diſobedience, to remember the King of that Vote of Parliament, which Declared <hi>The Legality of excluding Him from the Inheritance and Succeſſion to the Crown.</hi> Or that which Declared <hi>All thoſe to be reputed and taken as Enemies to Parliaments, who ſhould lend the King any Money:</hi> And yet ſuchas this, is the beſt Authority you produce for us to depend upon, and to juſtifie our preſent manage againſt His Majeſty, before God and the World.</p>
            <p>Well, what is it then the Parliament (as you call it) in 72. Declared il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited Toleration, you ſay; was that all? The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and latitude of the Indulgence then Granted, againſt which they excepted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I believe it was rather the Authority, on which it was founded; if an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and Unlimited Toleration be all, againſt which you except. From whom, or what part of the Diſſenters, would you have His Majeſty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Indulgence, to make it ever the more Legal on your Principle, to the reſt. I doubt your Parliament of 72. would not have thanked you for this: But let that paſs among your other Inconſiſtencies with yourſelf, into which I perceive you often unwarily fall. Whatever was done then, here, I am ſure His Majeſty by expreſs words in the Declaration, is ſo far from excluding His Parliament from their ſhare, either in the Authority of paſſing it into a Law, or of the Wiſdom and Council to be uſed, within what Latitude or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to bound it; as he refers all to the Concurrence of His two Houſes in Parliament.</p>
            <p>As for the Univerſality, and Unlimitedneſs of the Toleration, if that ſo much offend you, and that you and your Parliament of 72. place all your Illegality of the King's Indulgence there. I hope you will have content with a little patience, there ſhall be no Toleration of Vice, of Blaſphemy, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, and Profanation of the Lords day, as I hear ſome complain; there is none, I am ſure, intended now. However, the Toleration at preſent, is to be accounted on that ſcore; but in the nature of an Interim, or Suſpenſion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43628:10"/>as the State of things will permit, till ſuch a meeting of the King, with his Parliament for a further Regulation.</p>
            <p>But this Reaſon is not done with yet, for ſuch a Toleration is not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Illegal by the Parliament of 72, but condemned by the Church in all Ages.</p>
            <p>I wonder, Sir, how you come ſo Heterogenouſly here, to yoke together the Parliament of 72, and the Chriſtian Church of all Ages.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have thought, that would have ſorted better with a part of it ſelf, the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, do you know of any unkindneſs between them, that having in your firſt Reaſon, ſo fair an occaſion to have brought them in, and have ſet them down by our own Church, as both agreeing in the ſame Sentiment.</p>
            <p>You have rather choſe to place them in the Parliament of 72, as if they were Members of that; but that I could forgive you, if you had not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded with Repreſenting them Falſly, to have condemned ſuch a Toleration in all Ages, as the King has Granted by His preſent Declaration.</p>
            <p>If you did but uſe your ſelf a little more to Think before you Write, it would have been obvious to you, from the account, the Scriptures give of the Firſt Age, that you had ſtumbled at the Threſhold.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour himſelf, the Head of the Church, gave an early check to that manner of Spirit.</p>
            <p>As for the deſcending Ages of the Church, I have given you under the Head of your firſt Reaſon, ſome account, how matters ſtood in the Age of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> with reſpect to Toleration, and refer you further to other Pens, who have induſtriouſly treated on this Subject, and have ſufficiently ſhewed your Error.</p>
            <p>If you mean, that the Chriſtian Church in all Ages did never ſo Tolerate Diſſenters, from Her declared Doctrines, as not to note and diſcover them, and expoſe them to her <hi>Anathema</hi>'s. I grant you all this: In Gods Name, let not the Church ſpare Her Cenſures: The Declaration pretends not to take from them any thing of their own; I mean, their Spiritual Power, but only to Suſpend ſuch Temporal Penalties as belong to him only to inflict: Which is a thing ſo far from being condemned by the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, that the firſt. three Ages were merely Paſſive themſelves, and as in no diſpoſition, ſo in no condition, to inflict Temporal Penalties upon others.</p>
            <p>In the three following Ages, indeed, when the Emperors themſelves became Chriſtians, they had not only the favour and protection of the Laws for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but the Civil Sword alſo ſometimes turned upon their Adverſaries, but this was precarious only, and of ſpecial Grace and Favour, for which they were Thankful, and not pretended a ſtanding and unalterable Law, by which Princes were bound to it whether they would or no, and with whatſoever ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their Perſons, diſturbance of their Governments, or regret to their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>As for the other ſucceeding Ages of the Church, after the Sixth Century, the Church of <hi>England</hi> throws them aſide as no Precedents for us to follow.</p>
            <p>And yet it is the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, you would call in to avouch for you the Illegality of this Toleration.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43628:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. Your next Reaſon, on which you ground your ſuppoſe that we cannot Conſent, you thus expreſs,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is to Teach my People, that they need never come to Church more, but have my free leave, as they have the Kings leave, to go to a Conventicle or to Maſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, Sir, that they would do without the Kings leave, or yours either, before this Declaration came out.</p>
            <p>However, you are loth to have your Scepter wreſted out of your Hands, though it be with as vain and empty a Title, as King of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a Grand Seignior you may be ſtill in your Pariſh, I cannot tell; but I aſſure you, in our Country Pariſh Dominions, ſuch a deſpotick Church-Power is extinguiſhed long ſince.</p>
            <p>Well, Sir, I perceive you are not inclin'd to be ſo merciful a Prince over your Subjects, as His Majeſty over His, they ſhall never have leave for you.</p>
            <p>But your Brother King would intreat however this favour at your Hands, that when you have occaſion to ſhake your Rod over your Subjects, you would not ſend for him to be your Beadle.</p>
            <p>And the rather, becauſe, as he has no mind to it, and that it is againſt his Conſcience, ſo you have no want of him neither, the Spiritual Power having a Rod of their own, more proper and agreeable to their purpoſe, that is, the Rod of Excommunication, and other Church Cenſures, which no body goes about to take out of your Hand.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, when you Read the Declaration, you may let your People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, (if you pleaſe,) that it is with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> to that, and ſo you have well enough eſcaped the Danger, you fear ſhould enſue to your Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it would be to Teach your People, that they need never more come to Church, but have your free leave, as they have the Kings leave, to go to a Conventicle or to Maſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs on to your Fourth Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is, you ſay, to Teach the diſpenſing Power, which alters what has been formerly thought the whole Conſtitution of this Church and Kingdom, which we dare not do, till we have the Authority of Parliament for it.</p>
            <p>At the Kings Command you dare not do it, till you have the Authority of Parliament for it. It ſeems then however you are bound in Conſcience not to approve of ſuch a Declaration: Though it be againſt the Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nay, though condemned by the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, though againſt the Laws of God, and the Laws of the Land; yet Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parliament can diſcharge you of all.</p>
            <p>Never was any Pope in <hi>England</hi> ſo high, as Authority of Parliament is now ſet up, that can diſpenſe with the Laws both of God and Man; for all this of the Kings doing is againſt both, you ſay, but not of the Parliaments. By the way, though you give a fair Hint unto the Parliament, of the only Expedient, as things now ſtand, for the Common Peace, Agreement and Satisfaction of all, which is, by their concurring with His Majeſty in the ſetling what He has propoſed by His Declaration. For one part of the Nation approve of it for it ſelf; and all the reſt want nothing, it ſeems, for their intire Satisfaction, but only their Authority along with His Majeſties.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43628:11"/>
            <p>At the preſent the main thing you ſtick at, is, The Kings Diſpenſing Power without Authority of Parliament: Which indeed is the only thing you have ſaid which bears any ſemblance of excuſe for not conſenting, and conſequently not reading, the Declaration. And you would have done better to have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained your Poſt here, than to have ſtuffed your Letter with <hi>Enemies, Evil Counſellors, Popery, Maſs, Ruine, utter and avoidable Deſtruction to both Church and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been fain to follow you hitherto in this wild Ramble, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe, but to inflame and exaſperate Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, People, and all againſt the King, and make the Breach wider than it would be. Was not his late Majeſty, who was a Proteſtant, and by the Advice of Proteſtant Councellors, the adored Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> and others, forced to do the ſame thing, when neceſſity of Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs required it? Yet no Ruine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> followed, nor of the Proteſtant Religion, no Ruine, no Deſtruction, no Introduction of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, nor intended to follow. Some ſtir was then about the buſineſs of the Diſpenſing Power; but nothing to what it is now. Let us but quietly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the expectation of a Parliament, and that is a thing which it is likely may cloſe of it ſelf; It did ſo before.</p>
            <p>For indeed the Concurrence of His Two Houſes of Parliament, of which His Majeſty made no doubt, (as He ſays,) when He firſt iſſued out His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, before we had royld the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Concurrence, I ſay, of His Parliament, will bury up all in Silence and Peace, which is better than blow up ſo great a Flame, as would ariſe by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Coals of this Conteſt.</p>
            <p>Prerogative of the Crown, and Priviledges of Parliament, are Matters too Auguſt, for private Men as we are, to meddle in, much more to paſs Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, as your Letter does, and plainly ſay, The Diſpenſing Power is againſt the Laws and Conſtitution of this Church and Kingdom: That it is Illegal, which is ſo high a Preſumption, as can have no countenance for what was done in Parliament 72; for they have the Priviledge of free ſpeaking there: But out of Parliament perhaps it is a Crime of an higher Nature than we are aware. Even the Biſhops themſelves, though Perſons moving in ſo high a Sphere, and protected by ſo great a Power as the Pope was then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> yet they are given to underſtand, as I find ſome Lawyers note, 18 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. That for as much as they hold their Baronies of the King, that if they intermeddle with the Rights and Prerogatives of the Crown, they muſt look to forfeit their Baronies for their Preſumption. If, I ſay, the Biſhops out of Parliament incur ſo high a Cenſure, ſhould they do any ſuch thing, what Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion is due to Men of a lower Order? Evil Men, ſuch as have ſome Fiſh to take, which will not be catch'd but in troubled Waters, are wont to throw in one of theſe, as certain Occaſions of it, and as Bones of Contention whenever they have a mind to have one. It would have becomed us, who are Men of Peace, of all Men in the Kingdom, to have contained our ſelves, and, whatever we think, to have ſaid nothing in this Matter.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43628:12"/>
            <p>Now is Out-cry againſt <hi>Prerogative;</hi> Time was, when we made as loud a Cry againſt <hi>pretended Priviledges of Parliament, Liberty of the Subject,</hi> and for <hi>Prerogative.</hi> Among other Complaints and Grievances, which the Black Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament put into a Remonſtrance, and Preſented to <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, was, <hi>Frequent Diſſolution of Parliaments, Raiſing of Ship-money, Suſpenſions, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications and Degradations of divers Painful, Learned, Pious Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi> There comes in at laſt, a Complaint of His <hi>Chaplains,</hi> and other <hi>Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Preaching before the King, againſt the Liberty and Property of the Subject, and for the Prerogative of the King above the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What will the World ſay of us, while they ſee us, blow hot and cold out at the ſame Mouth?</p>
            <p>For my part, I beleive, the ſcratch is now, where it don't itch: Prerogative is not the thing does ſo much aggreive us. If it happened to be on our ſide, as we apprehend it now againſt us, we ſhould like Prerogative well enough. If we had liv'd in thoſe days, what ſhould we have though of ſuch a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative-Indulgence from Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> in the behalf of Her Proteſtant Subjects, from the Penal and Sanguinary Laws, then eſtabliſhed by Parliament? Would we not have dared to own it, to publiſh it in our Churches and Chapels, till we had Authority of Parliament for it?</p>
            <p>Would we have deſerted and oppoſed ſo gracious a Queen, and ſtroke into a Confederacy, with the concurring Opinions of the Nobility and Gentry, <hi>That to take away-the Penal Laws at that time, would be but one ſtep from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing of Proteſtancy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not find the Clergy at all aggrieved at the Diſpenſing Power, when at any time ſerving for the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion. For inſtance: When King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, by his mere Prerogative, diſpoſed of the Crown, for that Reaſon, to the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> moſt expreſly contrary to a late eſtabliſh'd Law paſſed in Parliament, whereby the Crown was entailed on the Children of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, of which, <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were both ſurviving, it was ſo far from a <hi>daring not to do it, till we had Authority of Parliament for it, and from ſcrupling the Teaching, of that, which alters, what has been formerly Thought the whole Conſtitution of this Church and Kingdom,</hi> That Doctor <hi>Ridley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> by Order of the Council, Preached a Sermon on purpoſe, at <hi>Pauls-Croſs,</hi> to ſet forth the Title of the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> and to juſtifie the proceedings of the King and Council in that Affair. Doctor <hi>Cranmer,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> was one of the Principal in the Council, and moſt of the reſt of the Biſhops and Clergy complied with, and approved of it, and commended it to their People.</p>
            <p>Nor were the Nobility and Gentry averſe from it.</p>
            <p>After Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the ſame Eſtabliſhed Laws, the Succeſſion of the Crown was to paſs to <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots;</hi> but ſhe being a profeſſed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, what intrigues were driven to exclude Her, in favour of the Proteſtant Religion, and alſo Her Son <hi>James</hi> the Firſt of <hi>England,</hi> yet in his Infancy, (and probably enough) ſuppoſed to bring with him His Mothers Religion?</p>
            <p>Did not the Parliament offer to the Queen, (I cannot tell, but it paſſed to an Act,) to enable Her to nominate Her Succeſſor to the Crown? <hi>Was not this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43628:12"/>to alter what had been formerly thought, the whole Conſtitution of this Church and Kingdom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, the Proteſtant Martyr, authoriſe the Canons of the Convocation 1640, by His Prerogative-Royal, the Biſhops and Clergy rightly aſſerting and eſpouſing His Authority and Power in that matter; nevertheleſs, for the Parliaments declaring at the ſame time the Illegality of the thing, and <hi>That it was againſt the whole Conſtitution of this Church and Kingdom.</hi> So that it is not ſo much the Parliament of 72, nor the Conſtitution of the Church and Kingdom, but ſomthing elſe in the Wind, which makes us ſo off the Hooks with Prerogative and Diſpenſing Power, at this time; ſomething we fear, which I am confident upon the Integrity of His Majeſties promiſe, we have no cauſe to Fear.</p>
            <p>But ſince you have ſo rudely jogg'd Prerogative, for nothing in the World, that I can ſee, but happening to ſtand in your way at this time, I will try a little of my skill, as well as I can, to defend it: Treating firſt of the King's Diſpenſing Power in general: And Secondly, of the exerciſe of it in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtance, which is the matter of the Declaration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In General.</p>
            <p>That ſuch a Power of diſpenſing with the Laws, at leaſt, in the interim of Parliaments be lodged ſomewhere, is grounded upon the ſame reaſon, as of making Laws, which is for the common good.</p>
            <q>Salus populi eſt Suprema Lex.</q>
            <p>Laws abſtract from the Sanctions, whereby they are injoyn'd, are nothing elſe but Proviſions made, as at the firſt; ſo on every ariſing occaſion of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the common Good, and conſequently, of averting any proſpect of evil.</p>
            <p>But for Parliaments, in which ſo great a number of Men are employed, and at ſo great a charge as that muſt be to the Nation, to Sit continually watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and waiting upon ſuch contingent occaſions, were almoſt as intolerable as any other evil the Laws would prevent. Somtimes Laws Salutary, and fitting to the juncture wherein they were made, with ſome unexpected Providence, Viciſſitude, or other un-thought Emergency, change their nature, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come noxious. Beſides that, many Evils, even pernicious, and deſtructive to Common-wealths, are ſomtimes ſo ſudden and impendent, as the Remedy would come too late in that way. Somtimes of that nature, that, as nothing but diſpatch, ſo nothing but Secreſie can avert them. Somtimes ſo fixed in a popular miſtake, and miſunderſtanding, as nothing but Time, and Reaſoning can make the diſcovery, and generally enough, diſpoſe the Nation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a Remedy. And what, muſt the Publick ſuffer perhaps an intolerable Evil, or an irrepairable Ruin, for want of applying an extraordinary Remedy in ſuch Emergent caſes?</p>
            <p>That it is not expedient only, but neceſſary for the publique Good, that a Truſt be repoſed ſomwhere, to make proviſion for the ſecurity of the whole Poplitique Body, in ſuch grand Emergencies, and to judge of the matter, and of the means proper for averting the Evil; I think, is by no body denied; Whether it be ſo in our written Laws, it makes no matter: I am ſure, he that runs may read it in the original Prototype of all Laws, which is right
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43628:13"/>Reaſon, even in the Fundamental Laws, and Conſtitution of this Kingdom, and all other Human Societies.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of 41. could ſee a diſpenſing Power thus far, thô they could not, or, which is blinder, would not ſee to ſet the Saddle on the right Horſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is reſolved, (ſay they, by both Houſes) that in this caſe of extreme danger, and of His Majeſties refuſal, the Ordinance, agreed upon by both Houſes, for the Militia doth oblige the People, by the Fundamental Laws of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being ſo then, that by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, written, or unwritten, ſuch a Diſpenſing Power with the preſent eſtabliſh'd Laws, is neceſſary at ſome times to be interpoſed. I know not, nor do I believe that any one elſe can tell me, where it can be wiſer and ſafer lodged, than in the Care and Conduct of the King. The whole Government was by the People at firſt entruſted to no other Law, but the confidence they had in the Love and Wiſdom, and Care and Conduct of their Princes: And if it proved other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they expected, there was no remedy but Patience. <hi>Ferenda ſunt regum ingenia,</hi> ſays <hi>Tacitus;</hi> and perhaps much better than <hi>Parliamentorum Ingenia, ut Sterilitas, &amp; caetera naturae mala.</hi> As unfruitful Seaſons, and other Evils of Nature we cannot help.</p>
            <p>When the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> asked of <hi>Samuel</hi> a King to judge them, and to go out before them, and fight their Battels, like as all the other Nations had round about them. <hi>Samuel</hi> told them, what would be the manner of ſuch a King as they deſired, like to the Kings of other Nations.</p>
            <p>1 Sam. 8.11. <hi>He will take your Sons and appoint them for himſelf, for his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and to be his horſemen, and ſome ſhall run before his chariots.</hi> 12. <hi>And he will appoint him captains over thouſands, and captains over fifties, and will ſet them to ear his ground, and to reap his harveſt, and to make inſtruments of war, and inſtruments of his chariots.</hi> 13. <hi>And he will take your daughters to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionaries, and to be cooks, and to be bakers.</hi> 14. <hi>And he will take your fields and your vineyards, and your olive-yards, even the beſt of them, and given them to his ſervants.</hi> 15. <hi>And he will take the tenth of your ſeed, and of your vineyards, and give them to his officers, and to his ſervants.</hi> 16. <hi>And he will take your men-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and your maid-ſervants, and your goodlieſt young men, and your aſſes, and put them to his works.</hi> 17. <hi>He will take the tenth of your ſheep, and ye ſhall be his ſervants.</hi> And ver. 18. <hi>Ye ſhall cry out in that day, becauſe of your king; which ye ſhall have choſen you, and the Lord will not hear you in that day.</hi> This might be the manner of Kings, you ſee, even of Gods own allowing, <hi>v.</hi> 22. And againſt whom, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.6. Even <hi>David</hi> himſelf dare not ſtretch forth his Hand; yet ſuch a Government God protected and owned, and was generally the manner of Kings, both with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and all other nations.</p>
            <p>Such Governments the Goſpel found eſtabliſhed generally over the world, and to ſuch Chriſt himſelf was ſubject, and owned ſuch as a legal Government, by paying Tribute to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> To ſuch Principalities and Powers <hi>St. Paul</hi> would have Chriſtians put in mind to be ſubject, and ſuch Magiſtrates to obey. And ſuch as was then the Imperial Authority of the <hi>Romans,</hi> it is more than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, was the manner of Government, taken up, and continued by ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43628:13"/>Princes, into whoſe hands the ſeveral parts of the Empire were broken after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>As for our Princes of this Nation, that they were not admitted to their Regal Authority, by Compact with the People, and on performance of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants or Laws to them; (to omit other Arguments at preſent) has ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidence, that our Laws have been all along, and are at this day impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated from His Majeſty, by the humble Requeſt, and Petition of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives in Parliament; Bargains do not uſe to be driven, but Favours begged in that precarious ſtyle. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> will hereafter turn a deaf Ear to our Requeſts, when they underſtand what we ask of them, is by degrees to part with, and ſteal away their Prerogative, and by every new Law they Grant us, to make themſelves ſo much the leſs Kings. It is no wonder, that our Kings have been in theſe later days ſurprized, they have not been aware of the Train laid, to cauſe them to diminiſh their own Power, and by little and little to Grant away their Crown, and leave nothing but that which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of it ſelf turn into a Common-Wealth: This is a Mine underground, in which there have been a long while, and are now more Hands at Work than over before. Engliſh-men have not heretofore wonted to be ſo diſingenious toward, their Princes, and it can be for no good end, that with ſuch obdurate Stiffneſs, ſome have hardned others againſt all compliance with His Majeſty to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, or but to endure the Suſpenſion of a Law, by which Himſelf, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps two parts in three of the Nation, is incommoded and aggrieved, and by parting with it, no injury done by the reſt; while they know too, in the mean time, that it is all by His Indulgence and Favour, that they have had, or can have for the future, the grant of ſuch Laws as they want for their own Accommodation: And that it is in His Power to hinder the Revocation or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of the ſame Laws, when we complain never ſo much of their Evil or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expediency.</p>
            <p>It may come in the way of our Princes ſhrewdly to Retaliate this our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice towards Them, as well as Ingratitude and Inſenſibleneſs of their Favours.</p>
            <p>They are ſuch Meaſures, as we would not have meted to our Selves.</p>
            <p>However, it is, and of Right ought to be, in the Power of His Majeſty, to help Himſelf, if we will not: And that will appear from what I have ſaid, that our Laws are all Acts of Grace and Grant from our Kings. Many of them are ſuch, whereby he has Graciouſly vouchſaf'd to diveſt Himſelf off, and releaſe the Subject from part of that Abſolute and Arbitrary Power, which the King had over us in thoſe inſtances, and wherein they complain'd and begg'd to be delivered of the uneaſineſs. Others, are Grants and Condeſcenſions in comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with us, for the promoting our Good, or averting the proſpect of ſome pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Evil.</p>
            <p>In all which Grants, as it is certain, that as the King at preſent apprehended no evil to Himſelf by them, (for elſe he would not have granted them,) ſo when he admits them to paſs into Laws, it muſt be ſuppoſed with a Reſervation of His Prerogative and a Power of Diſpenſing with them, in all ſuch Caſes or Emergencies, as they ſhall appear to be ſo afterward. Eſpecially in matters of ſo high concern, wherein His Life either Temporal or Eternal is indangered, I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43628:14"/>mean His Perſon or His Conſcience. And though with other leſſer inſtances, our Kings do for the moſt part Graciouſly bear, for the quiet and content of the People; yet in ſuch as theſe they cannot, they ought not to forbear the uſe of their Royal Prerogative.</p>
            <p>With this Caution and Reſervation, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> notes the Laws granted to the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> by himſelf and other his Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnibus a nobis dictis, Imperatoris excipiatur fortuna, cui &amp; ipſas Deus leges Subjecit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all thoſe before recited Laws, (ſays he,) the Fortune of the Emperor is to be excepted, for to that the Divine Providence over Princes, has ſubjected the Laws themſelves.</p>
            <p>This therefore take along with you as a thing of moſt remarkable Note, That for as much as the King is, as it were, the Vitals, the Soul and Centre of the whole Body Politique; whatever does tend to the indangering the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of His Perſon, the retrenching His Power, the violating His Honour or His Conſcience, is to be judged of like Malign Influence on all, there can be no <hi>Salus Corporis,</hi> where there is not <hi>Salus Capitis.</hi> And therefore the like Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity to be provided for it, if need be, by the like extraordinary Remedies: That is to ſay, by the Prerogative, out of the common Rode of Parliamentary Proceedings. Diſpenſing in the mean time with the Obligation of all ſuch Laws as ſtand in the way of this otherwiſe inſuperable Difficulty; and ſuſpending the Penalties of them, till a fitting Seaſon, for a Convention of Parliament to take farther Order.</p>
            <p>Now at ſuch a Diſpenſing Power, and in ſuch Circumſtances, ſome, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are highly offended; They will not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it, though it be clear as the Dictates of Right Reaſon can make it. And not againſt Law, as they ſuggeſt, for it is founded upon the Supremeſt Law, the moſt Sacred and Fundamental Law of all Nations, which is, as I ſaid, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Populi,</hi> I mean of the Body together with the Head; for which in ſuch Junctures, he who would reject this, is to be intreated, that he would firſt enlighten the World with a Diſcovery of ſome ſafer and wiſer Expedient in its ſtead. And yet with how much Moderation and Princely Clemency and Tenderneſs, and eſpecially towards the Church of <hi>England,</hi> does His Majeſty exert this His neceſſary Prerogative at this time? Such as, I think, might have more eſpecially obliged them, above others, to an Addreſs of Thanks, among the reſt of His grateful Subjects,</p>
            <q>Bona ſi ſua norint.</q>
            <p>Well, having thus far cleared a Neceſſity of ſuch a Truſt, as we call Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, in the King, to be lodged ſomewhere, as a Proviſion againſt ſuch Contingencies, in all wiſely-conſtituted, and not ſelf-confounding, Societies; What remains now, is to vindicate His Majeſty in the Uſe and Exerciſe of it at this time as neceſſary.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. For the Preſervation of Himſelf. And,</item>
               <item>2. For the Common Good of All.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43628:14"/>
            <p n="1">1. For Himſelf, with reſpect to the Preſervation eſpecially of His Perſon and His Conſcience from outward Violence.</p>
            <p>But firſt of His Perſon: That His Majeſty Himſelf, in His Perſon, (with whoſe Safety the whole Government and the Publick Good is ſo complicate,) was, and would ſtill be, in apparent danger, if His Prerogative had not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with a Suſpenſion of ſome of the formerly eſtabliſhed Laws, is a thing of which any Man may be convinced, who is not reſolved otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>What is the Support and Safety of a Prince, eſpecially ſurrounded with a multitude of Enemies, but Power to ſuppreſs them by more, or at leaſt equal, Numbers? Now let any Man take the Meaſures of His Majeſties Power and Numbers, at the time of His coming to the Succeſſion of the Crown, with proportion to the Number and Power of thoſe who had given Him juſt Reaſon to ſuſpect and fear them as His Enemies, who had always been before His Brothers Enemies, His Fathers Enemies, had taken away the Life of the one, and narrowly miſſed the Deſtruction of the other, and that but upon Jealouſie of their Inclination; much more bitter Enemies to His Majeſty, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Declaration of Himſelf, and publickly owning the Roman Catholique Religion.</p>
            <p>Alas! His whole Strength, (except that of the Almighty God,) what was it, but a few Roman Catholiques, added to the Loyal of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> If it had been the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> we know how few they were, in reſpect of the Shoales of the Factious and Diſcontented. How often had they been over-powered and baffled by them in the Election of Knights, Burgeſſes, Sheriffs of the City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and no way able to ſupport their Intereſt againſt them, with their whole Strength?</p>
            <p>But how great a Defalcation of that is to be made from thoſe who adhered to His Majeſty, may be computed from the ſmall Number of thoſe in the Houſe of Commons, who ſtood with Him againſt the Excluſion-Bill on the one Side; And from the no ſmall Number of thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who were divided from the Loyal, in that Traiterous Practice of ſupplanting Him, by the Intruſion of the unhappy Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> into the Succeſſion, on the other Side.</p>
            <p>And though indeed, many of the Excluding Members recovered their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and their Loyalty, in the firſt Seſſion of His Majeſties Parliament, when they declared their adhering to him with their Lives and Fortunes, againſt the Pretenſions and Practices of the Rebels, yet could they not lay again the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they had Conjur'd up, the common People, I mean, ſo generally preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd by their Excluſion-Vote, that notwithſtanding His Majeſties almoſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Succeſs and Victory over them in the Weſt, they ſtill perſiſted in the Alienation of their Minds from their Lawful Prince; and no corner of the whole Nation, but was ſtuffed full of them, who were content to beleive the Duke of <hi>Mommouth</hi> yet alive, and that they ſhould have another day, to try their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, againſt his Majeſty in Rebellious Armes.</p>
            <p>Againſt this multitude, nevertheleſs, he doubted not but to ſupport Himſelf and His Crown, by uniting His Catholick Subjects, into one State-intereſt with thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> neither of them alone being ſufficient to make any conſiderable Balance.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43628:15"/>
            <p>To this purpoſe in the next Seſſion of Parliament he moved, that to have the benefit and Service of all His Loyal Subjects, and that none of them might be under any diſability for the future, that they would joyn with him in a Repeal of certain Acts of Parliament, made in the 25 and 30 of <hi>Carol.</hi> 2. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by certain Oaths, and Teſts and Subſcriptions, were required to be made and taken of ſuch as were admitted into any publick imployment.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of the Seate of things, and Circumſtances of His Majeſties Affaires, together with their Loyalty, ſo ſignally ſhewed in the former Seſſion of Parliament, made Him believe He ſhould not be denied, what to Him ſeemed ſo reaſonable and neceſſary for the preſervation of Himſelf and all.</p>
            <p>But inſtead of that, all He could obtain, was no more, than an Indemnity of what was paſt; for which they expected to be thanked of thoſe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, who had merited ſo much from His Majeſty, and the whole Nation, by their ſignal Service againſt the Rebels in the Weſt. Which was an Anſwer ſo ſurprizing to His Majeſty, as he told them, he did not expect from ſuch a Parliament.</p>
            <p>So that His Majeſties Meaſures being broken here, and finding himſelf by this defeat of his Expectation, much weaker and the Power and Confederacy of his Enemies ſtronger.</p>
            <p>And the Laws which ſhould in the firſt place preſerve him, as the Centre of the publick good, barring him of his juſt and ſufficient Defence.</p>
            <p>He is forced by his Prerogative, to provide for his own ſafety and His Friends, and to ſuſpend the force of ſuch Laws, as ſtood in the way of it, till the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be better diſpoſed to take a right underſtanding of the thing, and to make choice of ſuch Members of Parliament, by whoſe Concurrence the Proviſion for His Majeſties Safety might be made.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Church of <hi>England</hi> is hereby diſobliged, but who can help it, or is to be blamed for it? it was offered to them firſt, and rejected by them. Will they be neither perſuaded to afford His Majeſty, together with theirs, the Service and Aſſiſtance of His <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> Subjects, (of whoſe Loyalty there can at this time be no doubt) for His ſufficient defence, againſt His numerous and inveterate Enemies; nor yet allow him by His Indulgence of Liberty to their Conſciences, to win them to a Dutiful, and Peaceable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. Juſt ſuch an unſociable rigor as this, now in the Church of <hi>England</hi> towards the <hi>Roman Catholioks,</hi> was that of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> towards us, whom they then called Malignants, and which was the occaſion of bringing His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty <hi>CHARLES</hi> I. of Sacred Memory, to the Scaffold, and all upon piques and diſlikes one againſt another on point of Religion. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> had a mind to Save the King, and deliver him out of the hands of the Army, which they then called Sectaries, but this was morally impoſſible to be done by them, upon the ſtrength of their own ſingle Intereſt, without uniting to their aſſiſtance the <hi>Malignant</hi> alſo, as they termed all thoſe who ſtood well-affected to the King and Church; but by no means would they be perſuaded to any conjunction with the <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> when His Majeſties Life at that time depended upon it, and might have been ſecur'd by it; and even to the laſt point when the Army came up in their march towards the City with the poor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43628:15"/>Captive KING in their power, they obſtinately refuſed to take in any of the King's Party to joyn with them, notwithſtanding all their frequent offers and importunities, and notwithſtanding their own ruine along with theirs; chooſing rather to deliver up the Common Cauſe, than to joyn with the King's Friends in one common Defence. Nay, to bring the parallel ſtill nearer, when it pleaſed the Divine Providence to make ſome aſpect towards the Reſtauration of His late Majeſty <hi>CHARLES</hi> II. to the Succeſſion of His Royal Fathers Crown; ſo imperious, and ill natur'd were they ſtill towards the poor <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> and ſo reſolved againſt admitting them to any ſhare in the Honour and Intereſt of the Enterprize, (however, their former Fidelity to His Majeſty might commend them, and His Affair need them,) that after the Secluded Members were re-admitted, a Reſolution taken of Convening a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in order to the King's Reſtauration; before their Riſing they paſſed theſe two Votes; One, <hi>That all and every Perſon, who have Adviſed, Abetted, or Aſſiſted in any War againſt the Parliament, ſince</hi> January <hi>the Firſt,</hi> 1641. <hi>his, or their Sons, ſhould be uncapable to be elected to Serve as Members of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> And another, <hi>That no Man ſhould act as a Commiſſion-Officer, without Firſt Acknowledging and Declaring, That the War undertaken by both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in their Defence, againſt the Forces raiſed in the name of the late KING, was Juſt and Lawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can more nearly reſemble thoſe Oaths and Teſts, which have been, of late years, laid upon ſo many of His preſent Majeſties Friends; and no doubt, with the ſame Deſign, and in a then probable proſpect of His Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Crown, <hi>That if they ſhould fail of Excluding himſelf, yet at leaſt they might exclude a conſiderable number of His Friends from joyning their Force, and Aſſiſtance to the reſt, when He ſhould moſt need them; and ſo, one time or other, he might fall into their Power thus unarmed and deprived of His juſt and ſufficient Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubtle Projectors, and Contrivers of this Intrigue, it is likely are now off the Stage, but ſince many of thoſe, who, I believe, have not the leaſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt His Majeſties Perſon, are yet nevertheleſs ſo intoxicate with the fears and jealouſies they then imbib'd, that they are yet hardly ſober, and muſt have time to recover their debauched Reaſons. It is neceſſary in the mean time, that His Majeſty look to the preſervation of himſelf, and of them alſo, whoſe Loyalty is yet half aſleep, and who perhaps, when they are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter awake, will find reaſon to thank him for interpoſing His Prerogative, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their obſtinate Defence of a Law ſo unreaſonable and unſafe, and thank God too, for that Courage and Wiſdom, with which he has inſpired him, to preſerve both them and Himſelf, and the whole Nation, from their precipitate Folly.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, may, I think, ſatisfie any reaſonable unprejudic'd Man, of the juſtice and neceſſity of His Majeſties exerting His Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative at this time, and in the manner he has expreſſed in His Declaration, for the preſervation of Himſelf, the Head of this great National Body, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be touched with danger in that principal part, without a fatal evil to the whole; But with His Majeſties Perſon, I intimated alſo a <hi>Salvo</hi> for His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43628:16"/>and that by His Prerogative, if he cannot have it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Conſcience is the common anſwer on the account of which, the Nobility and Gentry do not conſent to His Majeſties Propoſals, for taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws.</hi> Is there not ſome regard to be had to the King's Conſcience, as well as other Mens? The King, no doubt, ſo ſincere and devout as he is, in the profeſſion of His Religion, accounts it a very high offence againſt God, and danger of Eternal Damnation to His Soul, to perſecute what He accounts the Truth, and to drive away, or terrifie any by <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> from embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it. Who does not?</p>
            <p>I believe alſo the inflicting of ſuch Penalties on any other for mere matter of Conſcience, is not without a great regret to His own. <hi>That Conſcience ought not to be conſtrained, nor People forced, in matters of mere Religion;</hi> are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words of His Declaration. Now all proſecution of Law againſt <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> or what other Diſſenters from the eſtabliſh'd Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> muſt be made in the King's Name; and all Warrants, for the execution of Sanguinary, Pecuniary, or what other kind of Mulcts, iſſue from His immediate Authority. So that no Man's Conſcience of the whole Nation is ſo nearly concern'd, nor ſo accountable to God for what relates to theſe Laws, as the King's Conſcience. I think no Man will ſay, that the King ought in the execution of ſuch Laws, to ſin againſt His Conſcience; or that we have ever the leſs obligation upon us to Own Him, and Obey Him as our King, and to comply with Him tenderly for the finding ſuch a temper, (if there be any better, than what He already offers) for the ſatisfaction of both His Conſcience and ours. Subjects may ſuffer for Conſcience ſake, and loſe ſome part of the priviledge of Subjects, rather than break the publick meaſures which have been eſtabliſhed. But Kings may not be conſtrained by Law to ſuffer, nor to diminiſh any part of their Royal Sovereignty, for that their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences cannot comply with the execution of ſome Laws made by their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors in matters of Religion. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, <hi>Lucius, Ethelbert,</hi> by the eſtabliſhed Laws, ſhould have perſecuted Chriſtianity, but then they muſt have done it againſt their Conſciences. <hi>Julian</hi> found Chriſtian Laws in the Empire, but he could not be bound by them againſt his Will, and retain the Authority of Emperor.</p>
            <p>What would you have His Majeſty do? bring in an <hi>Excluſion Bill</hi> againſt Himſelf? lay down His Crown and Scepter at your Feet, and turn Subject to ſerve you? Or would you have Him do worſe, proſtitute His Conſcience to your pleaſure, and act againſt the intereſt of His Soul, to ſerve yours of the World?</p>
            <p>Indeed, what would you have Him do wiſer and ſafer for His own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and gentler and kinder for ours, than what is imported in that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which we ſuppreſs, notwithſtanding His Majeſties Command to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it, and againſt which, your Letter endeavours to ſtir up the madneſs of the People, and to alienate their Hearts and Affections from ſo Gracious and ſo Wiſe, and ſo Religious a Prince.</p>
            <p>You would have Him perhaps repreſent the Buſineſs to His Parliament, and leave it with them to excogitate ſome expedient for this emergent difficulty.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43628:16"/>
            <p>Well, and what muſt He do in the mean time? Sin againſt His Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? No, ſuſpend: For Gods ſake then, what is this ſtir for? You know, Sir, His Majeſty has already attempted ſomething of this Nature with His firſt Parliament, but with no ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>If you anſwer, It was not probably to be expected then; The Nation had not time enough to bethink themſelves to take a Right Underſtanding of the thing, and to apprehend the reaſonableneſs of His Majeſties Propoſals.</p>
            <p>To all this I agree with you: <hi>Magna molimina tardè moventur:</hi> Matters of ſo great moment, and ſpringing from ſuch a ſurpriſing Viciſſitude of State, could hardly be ſo ſoon digeſted. Yet His Majeſty Diſſolved not that Parliament, till after He had condeſcended to Treat further of that Affair in His Cloſet, with moſt of the principal Members, and till He aſſured Himſelf of an utter averſeneſs in them to any reaſonable Complyance.</p>
            <p>If you ſay then, He muſt leave it to the iſſue of the next Parliament, after ſo long a time as they have had to think over again: You ſay right, and ſo His Majeſty intends, and ſo He would have us ſignifie for the Peoples Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by Reading this Declaration.</p>
            <p>Well, but in this longer protraction of the time to another Parliament, what would you have Him do? Put theſe Laws in execution, not only againſt the Safety of His Perſon, but of His Conſcience too? Perſecute what He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the Truth? Apply Force, where in His Conſcience He judges nothing but Perſuaſion to be uſed?</p>
            <p>I know no remedy for His Majeſties Conſcience in the interim, but a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuſpending and diſpenſing ſtill with ſuch Laws: Nor do I believe that you, or any Man elſe, can aſſign a better.</p>
            <p>Why, He may not then make known the Continuance of His former Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in his firſt Declaration; and why may it not be publiſhed by us, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Conſcience, and whoſe Duty it is of all Men to be moſt tender, and of all others, towards His Majeſties Conſcience? And why not in our Churches and Chapels, where we have inſinuated generally to our People our own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes in common with others, even almoſt the whole Nations firſt haſtily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up falſe Conception of His Majeſties Purpoſes?</p>
            <p>Rightly to inform His Majeſties Conſcience, ſo far as is becoming, will not be taken amiſs from us: But if we find Him at a Point, and that He is not to be moved from His Sentiment in theſe Matters; I am confident none of us dare, I am ſure ought not, to adviſe His Majeſty to ſin againſt His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, no more than we would do it our ſelves againſt ours.</p>
            <p>Upon which Conceſſion, we cannot fairly cenſure and oppoſe in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we do, His withdrawing His Authority from thoſe Laws, in the practice and proſecution of which His Conſcience muſt needs be violated. Theſe are the Straits into which our Gracious King is driven at this Juncture; He chuſes (according to His Judgment) to offend Man, rather than God: Can we blame Him? Nay, ought we not rather to applaud Him for it? We of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ought of all Men to lay our Hands upon our Mouths, and make no Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, nor give Him any Moleſtation on this account.</p>
            <p>It is our own Doctrine, in His Majeſties Application, while there are ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43628:17"/>Diverſities of Religion among us, and none more infallible than other on our Principles, and while Temporal Laws will be medling with them, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining their Controverſies; unleſs they could make it a Shoo to fit to every Foot, and to ſtretch to every Conſcience, ſuch Mutations and Troubles of State as we meet with now, are like frequently to return, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will ever and anon be off the Hinges, new Excluſion-Bills to be brought into Parliaments, new Plots, and new Subjects for almoſt every new Prince.</p>
            <p>To prevent ſuch Convulſions of State, and probably, at one time or other, Diſſolutions of the Government, as new Religions and new Conſciences now a days multiply, His Majeſty wiſely propounds, that there be henceforth no diſability on account of Conſcience, as of Kings to Reign, ſo of Subjects to ſerve their Princes: In the mean time, nevertheleſs, for the ſatisfaction of our Conſciences, as well as His own.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty further declares, <q>That he is reſolved to uſe His uttermoſt indeavours, to eſtabliſh Liberty of Conſcience on ſuch juſt and equal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, as will render it unalterable, and ſecure to all People the Free Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Religion for ever.</q> And to thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and eſpecially the Proteſtant Religion, as by them profeſt, and as by Law Eſtabliſhed, he will protect and maintain ſupereminently above all others, as the National Religion: That as we ſhall give the Check to no other, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we be Checked by any in the free Exerciſe of our Conſciences; nor in the quiet and full enjoyment of our Poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>You would have His Majeſty continue to us, and protect and maintain us, in our Dominion, over all the Conſciences of the Nation; in the putting to Death, Baniſhing, Impriſoning, Confiſcating, and by all other means, (not to call it perſecuting,) ſuppreſſing and keeping under all others of a different Perſuaſion.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty, would lend us His Power and Authority, to do all this for us too; if in Conſcience he could, but I think we ought to excuſe him in that; and I hope all Perſons of Honour and Conſcience will tenderly, conſider His Majeſties Caſe as their own, and be ſatisfied that the King does no more in this Affair, than what any truly Conſcientious Man, even on our own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, muſt have done. And as Himſelf has been on this account hitherto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to ſuſpend the execution of the Penal Laws: and Teſt, ſo they alſo when convened together in Parliament, will find ſome Temper, that no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or oppreſſion ſhall for the future be laid upon the Conſciences of our Kings by our Laws; their Conſciences, as I ſaid, being much more concerned and aggreived in the Execution of ſuch Penal Laws and Teſts, by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then ours can be, who pretend that for the cauſe, wherefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comply with His Majeſties Propoſals for the taking them off.</p>
            <p>This I have ſaid, to juſtifie His Majeſty in the preſent uſe of his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as the neceſſary <hi>Salvo</hi> for His Conſcience in this Conjuncture.</p>
            <p>With His Conſcience, I further intimated a care to be taken for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his Honour, and that by his Prerogative, diſpenſing with ſuch Laws, as by any new emergency contrary to their Primary intention, do interpoſe and caſt a cloud upon it.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43628:17"/>
            <p>Honour in Noble, much more in Royal, Perſonages, is by our Laws ratable at the value of Conſcience, what therefore they declare upon their Honour, is Equivalent to what Perſons of a leſs Honourable degree, declare upon their Oath.</p>
            <p>But above all, the Honour of our Kings is a moſt ineſtimable Jewel of their Crowns, and Standard of their Government; it is upon the account of that, that their Subjects are diſpoſed to revere and obey them, to love them, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in them, to repoſe in them the truſt of all they are and have, and with their Lives and Fortunes to ſerve them.</p>
            <p>Upon which account it is, having ſo great an intereſt in the Government, and well being of Mankind, in their reſpective Societies, and ſo great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon Subjects to ingage them to a quiet and tractable compliance with the wiſe conſults of their Subjects; hence, I ſay, it is that God himſelf is concerned for their Honour, commanding in His Holy Scriptures, that as we <hi>Fear God,</hi> ſo we ſhould <hi>Honour the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me note to you further, that our Laws are, for theſe great Reaſons, ſo tender of the Honour of Kings, as they will endure no attainder upon them, but ſo ſoon as from Subjects, they become Kings, whatever attainder was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon them from the Laws, it falls of it ſelf, becauſe otherwiſe the Laws loſe their main end, laying a blot upon his Honour, and leſſening his eſteem with his People, from which does naturally ariſe many intolerable Evils to the Government.</p>
            <p>And for the ſame reaſon, whatever Perſon is Convict of an attempt to Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate from our Kings, the Affections of their Liege People, are looked on as Traitors, and reputed ſuch as do therein ſubvert the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, and if we follow the reaſon of the thing, for doubtleſs upon that the Law is Grounded, as any Perſon ſo any matter or thing, which tends to Alienate from the King the Affections of his Liege People, is by parity of Reaſon to be removed.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, that which we call the Teſt, however agreeable it might be to the preſent Circumſtances in which it was made; yet now, as Circumſtances are by the Divine Providence changed, the continuing of it does reflect ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour upon His Majeſty, as does evidently tend to alienate from Him the Affections of His Liege People, and that two ways:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As inſinuating Him to be a Conſpirator againſt the Life and Crown of His late Majeſty, in that which was called the Damnable Helliſh and Popiſh Plot. And,</item>
               <item>2. As implying Him an Idolater againſt God, the Supreme Majeſty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, That the Teſt was made againſt the Roman Catholicks, on preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, that they were generally ingaged in, or one way or other Abettors of, that then reputed Horrid Plot: I think is too plain to be fairly denied.</p>
            <p>If you object, That His Sacred Majeſty, then Duke of <hi>York,</hi> was Himſelf exempted from that Teſt, and ſo it could not reflect upon him.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Never the leſs for that. Nothing more ſerved their Purpoſes of that Conjuncture, than that ſubtle-ſeeming Tenderneſs of the Duke: For they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43628:18"/>knew His Majeſties Love and Confidence in His Royal Brother, was not yet ſhaken enough; and that to have but named Him among the other Roman Catholicks at that time, had certainly obviated the Kings Royal Aſſent to that Act.</p>
            <p>The Game was then but to extort from the King by force, or gain by ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, what they might eaſily convert to the Dukes Diſadvantage afterward. For the Teſt being put upon all bearing Office throughout the Kingdom, for the diſcovery of the Profeſſors of that Religion, on ſuſpicion and ſuggeſtion to the People, that they were all in that Conſpiracy; and the Duke being known to be of that Religion, every one knew how to draw the Concluſion, though the Duke were excepted, to pleaſe the good King; but eſpecially when Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were afterward intrigued to that paſs, that they dared openly to bring againſt Him a Bill of Excluſion in the High Court of Parliament, and infaming Him at the ſame time all over the Kingdom, with Libels of the moſt black and horrid import, that Craft and Malice together could ſuggeſt. Whatever was in the Deſign, it is manifeſt enough in the Event, that the firſt impoſing of this Teſt, and diffuſing it through the whole Kingdom, did univerſally fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a diſguſt and prejudice againſt Him, and caſt a Diſhonour upon Him, and was a Method and Diſpoſition to the Excluſion-Bill, which followed while He was yet Duke.</p>
            <p>But now He is, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame, and the frequent occaſion of uſing and renewing it, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily continue, renew and faſten in His Subjects Minds, the ſame precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived prejudice, which cannot be without Alienation of the Affections of His Liege-People from Him, and conſequently not only incumber and make His Government unwieldable in His Hand, but alſo ſhrewdly hazard a Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it; and be a continual Spring of many Evils, againſt all which, the keeping up of this Teſt ſtill, and putting that alone into the Ballance, I think muſt appear to any thinking Man, lighter than Vanity. And yet much more, when this malicious Suggeſtion againſt the King and others of His Religion, is by the ſame Votaries to this Teſt, for the moſt part acknowledged to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Sham and Illuſion, Cheat and Villany.</p>
            <p>It were to be ſuppoſed in generous Equity, that all thoſe who had on that account ſuffered in their Fortunes and their Honour, their Innocency being cleared, ſhould be alſo now cleared of the Laws reſpecting them on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and that ſome other expedient might be excogitated, ſo to ſecure us and our Religion, as might not expoſe innocent Perſons to Diſhonor and Ruine. How ſhould we expect God ſhould bleſs it to us, and make us ſafe by ſuch an unjuſt ſecurity: Unjuſt, (I ſay,) and eſpecially to ſo Great and Sacred a Perſon as our Prince.</p>
            <p>Why do we ſuffer any thing to remain, which may intimate and inſinuate to His Liege People ſuch a falſe Suggeſtion, and diſhonourable Imputation, and ſtill further impreſs upon their Minds ſo odious a Character, as in this <hi>Teſt,</hi> if not by deſign, yet by event, is evidently caſt upon him.</p>
            <p>From what has been ſaid on this Head, Firſt, with reſpect to that Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, you ſee the neceſſity of the King's aſſerting His Honour by His Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43628:18"/>at this time; ſeeing we do yet ſo tenaciouſly hold our Reſolution of retaining ſuch Laws: nevertheleſs, for the reflections from them, on His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Honour, and the evil conſequences of that, upon His Government.</p>
            <p>Another reflection on His Majeſties Honour, for the preſerving of which he is conſtrained to make uſe of His Diſpenſing Power, and particularly againſt that eſtabliſhed Law, called the <hi>Teſt,</hi> is this; That in the uſing of it, and ſo long as it continues, and ſo often as occaſion returns, for the iterating of it, His Majeſty is inferred, and publiquely marked for an Idolater. Which odious Inference, ſo perpetually injected into the Minds of the Mobile, it cannot but beget in them an Averſation from His Majeſty, and an Alienation of the Affections of His Liege People; making them turbulent, uneaſie, and unmanageble by the Government.</p>
            <p>You may ſay, perhaps, we cannot help that; People will think as they liſt.</p>
            <p>It's true, but in the mean time, I think, according to the maxims of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is neither politique, nor decent, that the Laws themſelves ſhould ſet a Brand upon the King, and adminiſter Fuel to their Fire.</p>
            <p>Though the People will not be Tongue ty'd, yet the Laws may, and ought, if, as I ſaid, they will be conſiſtent with themſelves, for that were a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, ſo ſeverely to cenſure whatever does alienate from the King, the Affections of His Liege People at one time, and yet admit, and encourage it at another; can ſuch Laws Honour the King, as the Scriptures have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, which do conſtrain all Men, before they can be capable of ſerving His Majeſty, aloud, and in open Courts of Juſtice, every where diſperſed over the whole Nation, and with the Sanction of a Sacrament, to declare their abhorrence, and renunciation of certain Doctrines, and Tenets of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by which they do infer His Majeſty to be a groſs Idolater: which Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines they nevertheleſs know at the ſame time, as by our King, ſo by moſt of the Princes of the Chriſtian World, to be conſcientiouſly owned and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
            <p>What higher contempt, affront, and diſhonour can there be put upon a King by His Subjects? and ſtill higher, That His own Authority ſhall be forced to juſtifie, and encourage, and give them only Rewards, and Honors, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for ſo doing; and to exclude all others, who think it becomes them to be more modeſt, and in ſuch a matter, to ſuppreſs their cenſure, and keep their Sentiment to themſelves. If His Majeſty ſhould require of us, with all this Solemnity, to Declare, that we believed the worſhip of the Hoſt, Invocation of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be no Idolatry, and that conſequently, neither himſelf, nor any of His Church and Communion, were Idolaters in ſo doing; what leſs oppoſition, and clamour of Popery could we make, than we do now, when His Majeſty only deſires, that we would take the liberty of Thinking, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing alſo modeſtly, what we liſt ourſelves in this matter, ſo we would not force others to make a publick Declaration of it, and ſolemnly to Swear to it too, who perhaps, are not ſo ſatisfied in the thing, or if they are, think it no good manners to His Majeſty, to do it at this time.</p>
            <p>The King would not exclude us, but admit all His good Subjects indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43628:19"/>to His Service, and His Favour; nay, the very <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhall not be capable of the like Places and Offices, but as they ſhall be bound and diſabled from doing any injury to others, or infringing the leaſt Liberty, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, or Honor of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>But by His Laws, whether He will or no, to conſtrain Him, to admit no other Perſons about Him, none to attend in His Houſhould, none to Serve Him in the Miniſtring of publick Affairs, but ſuch as have taken ſuch Oaths, as imply Him to be an Idolater!</p>
            <p>Shall he have no other Objects when ever he lift up His Eyes, or which way ſoever he look, but ſuch as may ſtir up in Him a regreting remembrance of the conſtraint, we put upon Him, and our ill uſage of Him?</p>
            <p>Theſe are things not to be endured by Bleſh and Blood; I am confident, no Gentleman in <hi>England</hi> could be content to make it His own caſe; nor will they, I hope, when they more nearly look into the thing, and ſee what evil conſequences it is likely to produce, Cenſure His Majeſty for uſing His Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Diſpenſing with ſuch Laws, till a fit time for the Convention of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that the rather, for that His Majeſty Declares His willingneſs to concur with them there to the eſtabliſhing any other Law, equivalent in its ſtead, which without thoſe oblique wipes upon His Majeſties Religion, His Honour, and His Conſcience, may be as effectual to ſecure us in the profeſſion of our Religion, as that we enjoy.</p>
            <p>And not only His Honour, but his Life alſo, may be in danger from this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation: There being no ſmall number of zealous Proteſtants, ſome of which I have met with, holding Idolatry to be a Crime puniſhable with Death by Chriſtian Magiſtrates; and ſome worſe than that, that every Mans Hand is to be upon them to put them to Death, that their Eye is not to pity or ſpare ſo much as an Inticer to Idolatry, though our own Father or Mother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſaid in Vindication of the diſpenſing Power, His Majeſty now uſes, as neceſſary for the Preſervation of His Perſon, His Conſcience and his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>And though, as I ſaid, what concerns His Majeſties, and the common good are ſo interwoven, as the publick muſt have ſuſtained a very great Evil, if not a probable Ruine and Diſſolution of the Government, by any Rebellious or violent attempt on His Perſon, ſo Naked and Defenceleſs, as we would have left Him, and that His Majeſty by theſe Meaſures, ſaves His Perſon, His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and His Honour.</p>
            <p>Yet, ſince His Majeſty has been pleaſed in His Declaration, to juſtifie the exerting of His Prerogative at this time, not only on the account of Himſelf, but of many other advantages which may thence accrew to His People.</p>
            <p>I ſhall deſire you to conſider them alſo, as they ſtand commended to us in the Declaration it ſelf, and with thoſe further enlargements on that ſubject, lately publiſhed from other Excellent Pens, to which I refer you.</p>
            <p>And go on to the next Reaſon, on the account of which, a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot, according to you, Conſent to the Declaration. In which, and the reſt that follow, I may be ſhort, for I reckon the buſineſs of your Letter is done. If I have cleared, in all wiſely conſtituted Societies, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43628:19"/>Reaſon and Neceſſity of a Power, diſpenſing with the eſtabliſhed Laws, in ſome extraordinary Caſes, without which, the publick Good, which is the main end of all Laws, and Governments, cannot be ſecured at all times, That ſome body muſt be truſted with this Power. That it is no where wiſer and ſafer lodg'd, than in the King. That therefore we muſt acquieſce in His judgment, when it is ſeaſonable to uſe it; That nevertheleſs, for our ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, the Reaſons which His Majeſty has given in that Declaration of His, which we refuſe to Read, are very clear and cogent, for the putting in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice His Prerogative at this time. But you ſay further, We cannot Conſent, nor Read. For that is to recommend to out People the choice of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as ſhall take away the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> which moſt of the Nobility and Gentry have Declared their Judgment againſt. This is an Argument, not from the force of Reaſon, but Example, which may be right or wrong, as it happens, and we have no way to aſſure us, when it is, and when it is not, but by putting it to the touchſtone of Reaſon; which being done already, till I ſee thoſe Reaſons anſwer'd, I have no more to ſay, but <hi>Magis amica Veritas.</hi> Passing this over therefore as nothing new, but only a ſcrape to the Nobility and Gentry; you ſay next, rather than nothing, almoſt the ſame over again, <hi>viz. That it is to condemn all thoſe great and worthy Patriots of their Country, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited the deareſt thing in the world to them, next a good Conſcience, that is, The Favour of their Prince, and a great many Honourable and Profitable imployments with it, rather than conſent to the Propoſal of taking away the</hi> Teſt, and Penal Laws, <hi>which they apprehend deſtructive to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and the</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion; <hi>and he who can in Conſcience do all this, I think need ſcruple nothing.</hi> If the ſame Propoſal had been made to us as to the Worthy Patriots, that is, Whether we would give our Votes in Parliament, for taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> then you had rightly taken an Argument a ſimili for our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like them, rather than conſenting, which is the thing you pretend to do, but very inconſiderately, for our Caſe is not like theirs. Nor will the Great and Worthy Patriots Thank you for bringing them to parallel and patronize your Diſobedience to His Majeſties plain Command, when the Conſent they were asked to give, was only to a Propoſal, and ſo can imply no Diſobedience, if they did not conſent. If His Majeſty had asked no more of them than he does of us, which is, to publiſh His Declaration; they would never have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited His Majeſties Favour for that, nor their Honourable and profitable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. For how, I pray, came His Majeſties Declaration the firſt time publiſhed; I ſuppoſe it muſt be communicated to others, ſo, as to paſs all over the Nation, through many Hands of Officers, of the Gentry, and of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility too, for any thing you know; and of ſuch, as nevertheleſs did ſtop, perhaps, at the Propoſal of taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> and ſo are you left free to do, if you pleaſe, for all your Reading, and as free are all thoſe that hear you.</p>
            <p>You proceed next, to the evil conſequences which may follow your Reading; It would make our Miniſtry contemptible, you ſay, which muſt by no means be admitted, right or wrong, for ought I ſee, <hi>A Miniſter muſt look to pleaſe and humour the Mobile, or all his Counſels, Exhortations, Preachings, Writings,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43628:20"/>are nothing worth.</hi> For <hi>St. Paul</hi> has ſaid, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Let no man deſpiſe thee?</hi> That is well enough argued againſt Authority, in a matter, where we ſee the People as hot, and as forward as ourſelves.</p>
            <p>But now, if we were to Teach the People, as you call it, by Reading the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> the Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> or the Book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> or any thing elſe, not ſo reliſhing; or by which, we are like to get the Ill-will and Contempt of the People: Why, it is but putting on our Noſe of Wax again, with a bent on the other ſide; <hi>then by honour and diſhonour, by good report and evil report, as deceivers and yet true,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.8. Am I therefore become your enemy, becauſe I tell you the Truth? If your buſineſs were only <hi>ad captan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum populum,</hi> this might ſerve; but whereas you wiſh us ſo to behave ourſelves, that no Man deſpiſe us, It will concern us, who are Clergy-men and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, not to appear to all Men of Senſe, ſuch ſilly and deſpicable Animals, as you ſeem to take us for, by thinking to impoſe upon us, with ſuch pitiful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry as this: For, Sir, Is the thing evil, or is it not? If it be, as ſomtimes you are in the mind, contrary to the Laws both of God and Man, do but prove this as ſoundly to us, as you have ſaid it temerariouſly, and we are as much at a point, for not recommending it to our People, as you, though they ſhould deſpiſe us for it never ſo much. But if it be not evil in itſelf, as, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting your Theme, in another place you had almoſt ſlipped out, in theſe words, <hi>It may be it were no fault, to conſent to the Declaration.</hi> If I ſay there be perhaps no fault, but only a popular miſpriſion in it, to make ſome Men deſpiſe us; by the ſame reaſon we ſhould not read the Book of Canons, as we are bound every year, nor an <hi>Homily,</hi> nor the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> itſelf.</p>
            <p>Your next Reaſon is, that it will effectually tend to the ruine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> And why? <hi>Becauſe it will provoke, or miſguide, all the friends it has; What, the Reading it, and nothing elſe?</hi> A Man had as good be a keeper of Bears, as of ſuch Friends, who will be ſo eaſily provoked. As for the King, no body cares how much he be provoked, though he be moſt able by His Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and obliged by His Sacred Promiſe, to Protect us from ruine. And if we once diſoblige Him from that, I fear we ſhall find it beyond the Power of the Nobility and Gentry, to protect and maintain us, ſo far as he has ingag'd Himſelf in this, ſo provoking, Declaration; ſuppoſing His Majeſty falſe and treacherous to His Royal Word and Promiſe; you have ſaid ſomthing on this Argument; and truly he who ſhould be over ſolicitous in anſwering it, would but ſeem to be ſo too. Wherefore, you may run for me to the end of your Rope, with the reſt of your harangue on this reaſon. It is all ſet on a falſe bottom; which is Anſwer enough.</p>
            <p>Your Objection comes next, of ſome who ſhould ſay, Theſe are Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but conjectural, and not abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may be the Reading of it will not ſo effectually tend to the Churches ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which you Anſwer, They are not indeed ſuch effects in reſpect of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, as ariſe from natural Cauſes, but they are as morally certain, as any thing can be. Good Sir, then do us the Favour but to hear them made out, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as evident Demonſtrations as you have promiſed us, let us ſee this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Certainty. Moral Effects muſt have Moral Cauſes; Is not the Kings a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43628:20"/>Moral Promiſe, and may not a Moral Certainty be grounded upon that? It ſeems you were before aware of this Retort, and you think fit to grant it, in theſe words which follow, which are by way of Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the King cannot keep his Promiſe to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>if the Teſt and Penal Laws be repealed?</hi> To which your ſelf make anſwer, <hi>You cannot ſay but this may be;</hi> ſo that you grant as Moral a Certainty on this ſide, as on the other. But the Kings Moral Certainty is not to be believ'd, though yours muſt: But for Reaſons wherefore, you are wont to be ſparing, where the Matter pinches; but if we will take your Word, there are ſome very ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ones behind the Curtain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>the Nation does not think fit to try it, and we commend the great Men who deny it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we will take ſuch Reaſons, as you think fit to make ſhow of at preſent, why here they are: The King is an Immoral Man, and therefore no Moral cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of what otherwiſe might be poſſible enough in it ſelf: The King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes an Immoral Religion, and he converſes with a ſort of Immoral Men, called <hi>Jeſuits, who can preſently furniſh him with a Salvo, for his inclination, to forget his promiſe to the Church of</hi> England: Is not this to make the matter almoſt as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a Demonſtration, as you promis'd us? Why, Sir, I confeſs this is a young Phoenix Argument, ſprung out of the Aſhes of that old one ſaid to be of the Earl of <hi>Shaftburies,</hi> which was burnt by the hand of the Common Hangman, <hi>We muſt have a King we can truſt:</hi> And the Nobility and Gentry are called to take notice of it, and to be ſuppoſed they go on the ſame ground; <hi>Nay, the whole Nation do not think fit to try it, you ſay.</hi> And all muſt be thanked, the Nobility and Gentry eſpecially moſt tenderly treated, and their Ears by no means grated with this Declaration, <hi>which may diſcourage, provoke or miſguide them from their oppoſition to the King on this account, and then we are finally ruin'd indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Church of <hi>England</hi> can be beholding to you, for furniſhing her Miniſters with an Argument againſt the Kings Declaration, which ſmells ſo rank of the Hangman; I am miſtaken in her, which I am ſure I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe who are Iſraelites indeed: Wherefore I think it needleſs to ſpend any more words about it. But having made ſure of the Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as you would have us think: Now but a word to the Wife, and you have done, and that is to the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who</hi> (ſay you) <hi>are ſo wiſe and conſidering, as out of our oppoſition to the King on this Propoſal, to ſmell in us ſomething of a perſecuting ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, how ſhall the Matter be handled then, that they be not provoked, for there is no Policy in that at this time of the day; however we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked them heretofore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Diſſenters,</hi> (you ſay) <hi>whom we ought not to provoke, will expound our not reading to be the effect of a perſecuting ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it ſeems, not reading is teaching too as well as reading; what you will for that. But how ſhall we ſplit the hair between the Nobility and Gentry on the one ſide, and the Diſſenters on the other? If we can draw both to to our ſide, nothing can reſiſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To diſoblige the Nobility and Gentry were more fatal indeed,</hi> as you ſay, <hi>than to anger the Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43628:21"/>
            <p>But they are numerous and rich, there is no parting with them at this time neither, ſome cunning and fineneſs muſt be uſed then to bring over the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Confederate Army; for God's ſake, what is the meaning of all this Plotting and Projecting, and making Leagues, and Alliances, and muſtering our Forces? Where's the Enemy? May a Man venture to peep his Head over the Wall to ſee this ſame <hi>Hanibal ad portas;</hi> which comes threatning thus with Fire and Fagot, to diſcharge our new Alliance, the Diſſenters, <hi>From all Pains, Penalties, Forfeitures, Impriſonments, by them, or any of them, incurred or forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or which they ſhall, or may at any time hereafter be liable to, by reaſon of their Nonconformity, or the exerciſe of their Religion, and from all Suits, Troubles or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances for the ſame;</hi> And as for our ſelves, there is no more mercy to be looked for at his hands, than for our Brethren the poor Diſſenters: <hi>For all our Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Clergy, and all other of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in the firſt place: Alas! they muſt be every Scul of them protected and maintained in the free exerciſe of their Religion, as by Law eſtabliſh'd; and in the full and quiet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all their Poſſeſſions, without any moleſtation or diſturbance whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is time, one would think, to project a way of joyning the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Diſſenters to keep one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For theſe Diſſenters are wiſe and conſidering Men, and they are ſenſible of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that all this is</hi> but <hi>Anguis in Herbâ,</hi> a mere Trap, a Gin, a pitfall. And although they deſire Eaſe and Liberty, they are not willing to have it with ſuch apparent hazard of Church and State. Let them but ſtay their longing a while; for when there is but the firſt opportunity <hi>of ſhewing our inclinations without danger, they will find that we are not ſuch Perſecutors, as we have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented.</hi> Where then, and what has been the danger that no ſuch Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have appeared toward the Diſſenters theſe twenty eight years back? Have not our Proteſtant Princes, as well as this, been always oppos'd in their Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to any ſuch Indulgence: King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second made them a Promiſe of it at <hi>Breda,</hi> he made ſeveral Intimations of that Promiſe in future Parliaments, and how his Honor lay at ſtake; but met with no Inclination in us unleſs it were, to lay on more lode: And after, when that gracious Prince was fain to breake from us by main force, and upon his own Prerogative iſſue out his promiſed Indulgence; he could have no peace with us again, nor any compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him in his other Affairs of State, till we almoſt compelled him to a Revocation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet what manner of Men ſhould the Diſſenters ſee we are towards them, if we had but opportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now you ſay, there is danger; yes, now we have carried our ſelves ſo, as to apprehend danger to our ſelves, there comes an opportunity for cokeſing the Diſſenters, to help us to turn the danger upon the King; and they muſt be made to believe, they are in the ſaddeſt danger now that ever they were, who in truth were never ſo much out of it for above twenty years paſt, nor in ſuch probability of ſhaking off the fear of any ſuch danger for the future, if they are not ſeduced and infatuated to be unthankful to their gracious King, and wanting to themſelves. Now the reaſon, wherefore I call the Diſſenters to look back upon our Inclinations towards them is not to cenſure the Wiſdom and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43628:21"/>Honor of thoſe Parliaments, which made ſuch Laws againſt Diſſenters as Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then ſtood.</p>
            <p>But to ſhew, that His preſent Majeſties Religion, which has been as ſevere to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Diſſenters as ours, may nevertheleſs for that be as ſincere as we can be, in the Inclinations he hints the Diſſenters may hope from us when time ſerves: I like your Commendations of the Church of <hi>England</hi> every where well enough, and believe their well meaning, but not as you make uſe of it, ſlily to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate a diſtruſt a ſnare, and to create a ſuſpicion in the Diſſenters of His Majeſties Veracity and Honour, and by this baſe Suggeſtion tempt them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert Him in this Juncture, and adhere rather to thoſe who oppoſe Him: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as much as you, that they are ſo wiſe and conſidering as to be ſenſible of a ſnare, and as likely of your ſetting for them, as of His Majeſties. And that they will think it more wiſe and ſafe to confide in His Word, than in yours; and to take the Opportunity which now preſents, than to ſtay and ſtarve while your Graſs grows.</p>
            <p>But leſt your Promiſes ſhould not prevail, you attempt alſo by Threatnings to deter them from ſtrengthning His Majeſties Party and Deſign. <hi>Should they take it in this way,</hi> you tell them, <hi>they will find it the deareſt Liberty that ever was granted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not deny, but Gold may be bought too dear; let us ſee, what we have by the Bargain of parting with our Teſt and Penal Laws. If all the Diſcourſe of your Letter had been againſt thoſe only, who are for delivering up our Laws into the Hand of another Religion, without any effectual ſecurity for our own; I ſhould have agreed with you, that we cannot Conſent but muſt Suffer in this way, and it is plain His Majeſty is of that mind too. His whole Declaration being a Propoſal of Terms and Compremiſe of Peace among His Subjects, of whatever different Perſuaſions, that none may hinder one another of the Free Exerciſe of their Religion, and full and quiet enjoyment of their Property, and if you are ſo ſuſpicious of Siniſter dealing, from His Majeſty, he offers to make our ſelves, by our Repreſentatives in Parliament, Umpire in the buſineſs, So that your Inſinuation is very Ungenteel and Rude towards His Majeſty, and ſavors more of a piquing ill-natur'd jealouſie, than any juſt fear that we ſhould find the Liberty now offered, the deareſt that ever was Granted: Theſe are the Reaſons, on which you ground your Magiſterial Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; That no Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> can Conſent to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and therefore cannot read it; how weak and inſufficient they are to eſtabliſh ſuch an Hypotheſis, and that therefore all you have built upon it, muſt come down with it, let the world judge, ſo that nevertheleſs for your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> can Conſent to the Declaration, and then I think, that he may Read it, no body will deny.</p>
            <p>Nay, and that he ought, <hi>in omnibus licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> to pay an active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>To anſwer the Command by a Paſſive Obedience, <hi>To ſuffer all that can be ſuffered in this World,</hi> (as you ſomewhere ſay) <hi>to be ſubject only and not reſiſt, will not ſerve the turn here.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:43628:22"/>
            <p>The giving our Body to be burnt, in this Cauſe, will not make us Martyrs. There is an Active Obedience due to all the King's Honeſt and Lawful Commands, by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, though the matter of the Command have not yet entred by a Parliamentary Law, for that is but accidental; we owe him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much upon the account of our natural Allegiance, founded in that Relation between King and Subject. If it be a Matter in which he is neceſſitated to uſe his Prerogative, all that we are bound to ſatisfie our ſelves in, is this; Is it a Moral Command? Is it not againſt the Laws of God, over which he has no Power of Diſpenſing, though it were to ſave His own, and the Lives of all His Subjects? If not, we are bound to it by our Natural Allegiance, by our Loyalty or Legality, which is not to be underſtood ſo <hi>ad Legem,</hi> as it is not due for Conſcience-ſake; ſave only in ſuch Inſtances where it is paſs'd into a Parliamentary Law. For Allegiance reaches to Law in a further Extent and Latitude than ſo, even to that Law, which Nature and right Reaſon teach, is founded in ſuch a Relation as King and Subject, and Political Father and Sons. Not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to that Law, which defends the Right, the Liberty and Property of the Subject, which is for the moſt part written becauſe it paſſes by Grant, and ſtands on Record, from the King: But to that Prerogative Law alſo, which is natural and unwritten, and cannot be granted away, becauſe it defends the Rights of the Crown, and defends the Majeſty Authority and Dignity of the Prince, and the Capacity, whereby he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all the Offices of a Father to his People.</p>
            <p>Do not we ſwear a Canonical Obedience to our Biſhops, <hi>In omnibus Licitis &amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtis?</hi> By what Law of the Land is this required? By no Parliamentary Law, but, as I ſaid, by the Law of Nature, rooted in that Relation he bears toward us of our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Father. But here is no place for a Diſcourſe ſo large and copious, as it ſhould be, on this Subject. All I mean by it here is this, That if the Matter of the Declaration be Moral, Honeſt, and Lawful, ſo far as Lawful takes in the Law of the King's Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as well as the Peoples Laws: We muſt pay an Active Obedience to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of His Majeſty, on the account of our Natural Allegiance: A Suffering for it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not reſiſting only, will not juſtifie us to God, by whom Kings Reign, and whoſe Power is Ordained of God. This I take to have been all along the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all this, it is poſſible, ſome of the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent. Some will not take the pains perhaps, and ſome have not the parts to think deep enough. Some, like Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, ſtand their Ground where they were firſt ſet, rooted by Education, and ſome as much by Prejudice. Some have their Reaſon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poured, by their Fears; and ſome, by their Intereſts. What then? May they not read the Declaration? Muſt the grand and important Affairs of State be all at a ſtand, till ſuch Perſons can be ſatisfied? Muſt their Wills be the Law in the mean time, and their Judgment the Standard of the King and Council, and the whole Nation? Muſt their Declaration in this Matter be publiſhed in all their Churches and Chapels, and His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's never ſuffered to come in at the Church-door? Why may not both Tales be told, and both Sides heard? This is not juſt nor civil dealing with His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Again, What if you cannot give an internal Conſent, or a Conſent of Approbation? Can you not read it with a Conſent of Acquieſcence and Submiſſion? That is all which need to be in a Subject, to Matters of this kind. When the King, in whoſe Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive it is to make Peace and War, ſets forth a Declaration, ſignifying His purpoſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War, ſuppoſe with the Dutch or French; May His Officers, in the ſeveral Places where this Declaration is to be publiſhed, ſuppreſs it, and refuſe to obey His Command, unleſs, according to you, they can approve the Matter of it, and be ſatisfied in the King's Reaſons and Grounds of the War? I ſee not, but, upon your Doctrine, there is more Reaſon for it here, than where you would inſtigate us of the Clergy to give ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pernicious a precedent to the whole Nation.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43628:22"/>
            <p>A Conſent of Acquiſcence and Submiſſion, as I ſaid, to the Wiſdom and Juſtice of the King, is enough in ſuch Caſes, and with no more than that, Armies of their Subjects do follow our Princes into the Field, with the expence of their Blood and Treaſure, and not ſtand bogling, as you would have us, at nothing but Reading or Publiſhing His Majeſties Declaration. On this Principle it will be hard for His Majeſty, on whatever juſt and neceſſary occaſion, to raiſe an Army among Diſciples of your teaching; Nay, it is a wonder, if ſuffered to proceed, that it does not disband that He has. There is rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Concurrence of all Judgments and Votes to the making of the Laws themſelves in Parliament, and ſo not ſuch a Conſent as we call internal. Nevertheleſs an external, or if you will, call it a permiſſive, Conſent, of all, to the Enacting and Publiſhing it as a Law. Now ſuppoſe any of the Members of ſuch a Parliament, giving the Charge at an Aſſize or Seſſions, in the Office of one of His Majeſties. Judges, or Juſtices of the Peace; muſt he paſs over, and omit the recital or reading of ſuch Laws, as he does not, in his own Judgment, approve, or to which he had before refuſed his conſent and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage in Parliament? Many of thoſe Breves, or Letters Patents, in the behalf of poor diſtreſſed Sufferers, to which we are required to excite the Peoples Charity, I have heard accounted by Clergy-Men little better than Cheats, and yet make no ſcruple of reading them, and that with a whatſoever Law, Statute, or Proviſion to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Innumerable Inſtances of this kind might be offered, if there were need, to ſhew, that he, who cannot conſent to the Declaration with a Conſent of Approbation, may yet read it with a Conſent of Acquieſcence and Submiſſion.</p>
            <p>And further, what if you cannot Conſent to the matter of the Declaration, or the Expediency of it, in it ſelf; can you not conſent to Read it, in the nature of a Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. Not as common Cryers altogether, but yet as Men, whom our Ordinaries, as well as the King, do make uſe of to theſe purpoſes: His Majeſty would have us ſignifie His Pleaſure, that he would Treat with His People, by their Repreſentatives in Parliament, concerning the neceſſity of His Suſpenſion of the Penal Laws at preſent; and about cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Overtures of Terms and Conditions offered in Exchange, for the Repeal of them for the future: All this is but by way of Propoſal; Conditions and Terms offered, and all the way with a reſerve to the Parliament. No abſolute Conſent is required, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conditional, if ſuch propoſitions be liked or can be made practicable.</p>
            <p>What if it be propoſed, to take of the Teſt and Penal Eſtabliſhed Laws? What is there in this contrary to the Laws of the Land? as you frequently, but raſhly, ſuggeſt. Is the Repeal of a Law againſt, and not rather agreeable to, the known Laws of the Land? As to the method, which the King uſes to this purpoſe, what can be objected againſt our Conſenting to that? If any Nobleman or Gentleman deſign the Repeal of a former Eſtabliſhed Law, his Method for the compaſſing his end, muſt be by making known his Mind and his Reaſons: Ordinarily Books are Printed and Publiſhed all over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to this purpoſe before the Convention of Parliaments, what does the King more in this matter than other Men? And ſo for Recommending by us to the People, ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſit in Parliament, as may comply with His Majeſty in the buſineſs of the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: What is it more than Propoſal? And what is it more than we ordinarily do for the Nobility and Gentry at their Requeſt. Do not Letters fly about, and Horſe and Man, all over the Country, Night and Day, for the Election of ſuch Perſons, as are by one or other Recommended to us. This His Majeſty deſires us to ſignifie by His Declaration, but yet leaves us free after all. And what is the matter now, we cannot declare to the People theſe and others His Majeſties Propoſals? We nor they are ever the more compelled or interpreted to comply with them.</p>
            <p>Again, What if we cannot fully conſent? Are there not many things done by us, both for our ſelves and others, but with an half, or a doubting Conſent? Do we not perform many Commands of our Parents, of which we are not ſo fully ſatisfied, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43628:23"/>for their Expediency, and ſometimes perhaps for their Lawfulneſs? And are not indeed almoſt all the Conſents of Men in their Converſes and Negotiations one with other of this kind? Does the reading this Declaration ingage us in an evil and unlawful A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as neceſſarily as your Simile of Fire burning Wood? Have we no Reaſon of the leaſt doubt in this Matter? Have we robbed the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> of all his Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? If there be, as I believe with the moſt there is, ſomething of doubt in the other Balance, then that is a good Rule which heretofore we uſed to commend to the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the buſineſs of Conformity: It is good to doubt on the beſt ſide; Let us fear we fin againſt God, by diſobeying our King. That we are to obey the King <hi>in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> is out of all doubt: Whether this Command of His be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawful, is not ſo certain. Away then with your Obedience, where you ſee you may be moſt certain: This was after our own Meaſures I am ſure once, if we have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no falſe Meaſures ſince.</p>
            <p>And further, If we cannot ſerve His Majeſty in this, with ſo intire a Conſent as we wiſh we could; Can we do nothing of Civility, of Honour and Reſpect? Does not this move us ſometimes to ſtrain a little out of our Byaſs? If this Declaration had been a Speech of my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s, or a Letter of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s, we had been ſo kind to make them as publick as we could. Some of us remember the Ordinances of the Black Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Proclamations of an Uſurping <hi>Oliver,</hi> and how (though I believe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what againſt our minds) a little ſlaviſh fear made us buckle to the reading them in our Churches, and to give Thanks, and faſt as demurely as the beſt of them.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems neither Love nor Fear can prevail with us, in the behalf of His Majeſty. If it were but to have expiated and retriv'd that Sin and Folly of our Ingratitude, when we, like Blocks, lay unmoved without the leaſt ſenſe of His Majeſties more particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to us, and when an univerſal ferment of Joy and Thanks transfuſed it ſelf over the whole Nation, but our ſingular ſelves. A ſtupidity, in which your Letter would tempt us to be hardned more and more. This, ſay you, muſt have ſerved in ſtead of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of Thanks, which the Clergy generally refuſed, though it was only to Thank the King for His Gracious promiſe, renewed to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in his Declaration, which was much more innocent, than to publiſh the Declaration it ſelf in our Churches. I remember one of the famous <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons, why the Clergy ſhould not Addreſs, was, that it would be but I thank you for nothing; and that His Majeſties promiſe was but a Superogation, over thoſe Eſtabliſhed Laws, which had done more for our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Security already, than he could add.</p>
            <p>Now I though it would have becomed wiſe Men, however happy at preſent, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how fickle and various Fortune uſes to be: Who knows, what back Friends the Church of <hi>England</hi> may have infuture Parliaments, as likely as heretofore in their moſt Halcyon Days, and how much we may have occaſion to be beholding to a <hi>Le Roy avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera,</hi> to obviate their Attempts. But this I conceive was not thought of in the Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Days, when our Manners to our King was much of that Cynical ſort as of <hi>Diogenes</hi> to <hi>Alexander, Pray, Sir, ſtand out of our Sun, and don't hinder us of that you cannot give us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, Sir, you for your part, in ſtead of mending one Hole, are like to make two; You are for no Addreſs of Thanks, nor any thing like it: Wherefore I pray God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Church of <hi>England</hi> from falling into the Hands of ſuch Botchers.</p>
            <p>For my part, I would adviſe them yet to Addreſs to His Majeſty, acknowledging their Errour, beg His Pardon, truſt in His promiſe and give him aſſurance, they are ready to Read His Declaration whenever He pleaſe to Command them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I ſhould not give this Counſel, if I were not their Friend, and, Sir, <hi>Yours.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43628:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
